{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Pope Leo I convinced Attila the Hun not to perform this kind of action. This kind of action\nwas done by Gauls following the 390 BC Battle of the Allia. In 410 AD, Alaric led an army of\nVisigoths in performing this action, which St. Jerome identified as the effective end of the\nEmpire. For 10 points, identify this action in which the \"eternal city\" is pillaged.",
      "answer": "sack of Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nobility serving under this dynasty followed the \"Table of Ranks\" to determine bureaucratic\nadvancement. This royal house came to power after three different \"False Dmitris\" were\nsuppressed during the Time of Troubles. For 10 points, name this house founded by Mikhail I in\n1613, which remained in control of Russia until the twentieth century.",
      "answer": [
        "Romanov",
        "Romanov Dynasty"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man secured recognition of independence at the Treaty of Lausanne, which ended the\ndeportation of his country's Greek minority. This founder of the Republican People's Party banned\nthe wearing of fezzes and introduced the Latin alphabet as part of the \"Six Arrows\" platform. For\n10 points, name this founder of modern secular Turkey.",
      "answer": [
        "Mustafa Kemal",
        "Kemal",
        "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
        "Ataturk"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Council of Trent mandated that Catholic realms adopt this standard, which did not arrive\nin Greece until 1923. It replaced an earlier standard named for Julius Caesar. When it was\nintroduced to Great Britain in 1751, monthly debtors cried \"give us back our eleven days.\" For\n10 points, identify this modern calendar named for the Pope who devised it.",
      "answer": [
        "Gregorian calendar",
        "Gregorian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "These people displaced an Iron Age culture known as the Villanovans. These people\nworshipped gods including Tin, Uni, and Cel, and they spoke a now-lost language whose last\nknown speaker was the Roman emperor Claudius. They legendarily provided the final three\nkings of Rome. For 10 points, name these pre-Roman inhabitants of the central Italian peninsula.",
      "answer": [
        "Etruscans"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the Hellenistic period, this deity was syncretized with Apis to form the god Serapis. The djed pillar\nrepresented the spine of this deity, whose wife searched throughout Egypt to find the 14 pieces of his body\nafter he was torn apart by his jealous brother, Set. For ten points, name this Egyptian god of the afterlife\nwhose consort was his sister, Isis.",
      "answer": "Osiris"
    },
    {
      "question": "King Godfred built the Danevirke as a defense against this ruler, and later this ruler concluded the\nTreaty of Heiligen with the Hemming. This ruler, who died of pleurisy, was succeeded by his son Louis the\nPious, and three of his grandsons divided his empire in the Treaty of Verdun. This ruler, who was advised\nby Alcuin of York, was crowned on Christmas Day by Leo III as Imperator Romanorum. For ten points,\nname this King of the Franks who was the first Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Charlemagne",
        "Charles I",
        "Carolus Magnus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During a military campaign in this modern-day country, a failed attack on Sari Bair began with\na breakout from Anzac Cove and cost Winston Churchill his job as First Lord of the Admiralty. The\nGallipoli Campaign was fought against Mustafa Kemal’s forces in what is now this country. For ten points,\nname this country that gained its independence after the fall of the Ottoman Empire and is now ruled\nfrom Ankara.",
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Turkey",
        "Turkey",
        "Turkiye",
        "Republic of Turkiye"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After a war with the Ottomans, this empire annexed Bessarabia and supported the founding of\nindependent Bulgaria. This empire annexed Khiva and Bukhara during the “Great Game” with the\nUnited Kingdom. In 1825, a succession crisis in this empire led to the Decembrist uprising of soldiers who\nsupported Grand Duke Constantine, who instead remained in Poland. For ten points, name this empire\nthat, in the 19th century, was led by three Alexanders from the Romanov family.",
      "answer": [
        "Russian Empire",
        "Russia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "George Miller’s work on this process and its “magic number” was criticized by later experiments\nthat demonstrated the value of “chunking” in this process. The ancient Greek and Roman “method of\nloci” was used to improve this process, and autistic savants are frequently mentioned for their ability to\nperform extreme feats of this process. For ten points, name this mental process that consists of encoding,\nstoring, and retrieving information about past events.",
      "answer": "memory"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) In what 1973 conflict did Egyptian forces assault the Bar Lev line while Israel was\nobserved the Jewish day of atonement?",
      "answer": [
        "Yom Kippur Wa",
        "Yom Kippur"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man ordered the building of a torture chamber with a beautiful exterior, known as his “hell.”\nThis man’s son, Mahinda, was sent on a proselytizing mission, and this man had the Mahabodhi Temple\nbuilt. This ruler built a structure, currently located in the Sarnath Museum, which is topped by four lions;\nthat column is inscribed with this man’s moral edicts. For ten points, name this grandson of Chandragupta\nMaurya, a devout Buddhist convert who ruled India in the 3rd century BC.",
      "answer": [
        "Ashoka the Great",
        "Ashoka"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Soldiers attacking this capital city during Operation Danube were deceived into thinking they were\noperating against fascist elements. In protest of human rights abuses, Jan Palach set himself on fire in\nthis city’s Wenceslas Square. A meeting in this city led to the the removal of Antonin Novotny as First\nSecretary and the ascension of Alexander Dubcek [doob-check], who began a series of liberalizing reforms.\nFor ten points, identify this namesake of a 1968 “Spring” uprising against Communism, the capital of\nCzechoslovakia.",
      "answer": "Prague"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler annexed Bavaria from Tassilo III and conquered Saxony from Widukind, massacring\nthousands of Saxons at Verden. He divorced his wife Desiderata in 771, then conquered her homeland of\nLombardy. This ruler, who established his capital at Aachen, is the subject of an Einhard biography. This\nson of Pepin the Short restored Leo III to Rome, who crowned him on Christmas Day 800. For ten points,\nname this King of the Franks and first Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Charlemagne",
        "Karl der Grosse",
        "Carolus Magnus",
        "Charles the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Immediately prior to this event, a character delivers a monologue in which he argues against a\npardon by stating “I am constant as the northern star.” A man justifies his involvement in this event by\ncomparing its central subject to a serpent’s egg. The target of this event is eulogized in a funeral oration\nthat begins “Friends, Romans, countrymen, lend me your ears.” For ten points, name this event in which\na Roman leader utters the dying words “Et tu, Brute.”",
      "answer": [
        "assassination of Julius Caesar",
        "Assassination of Caesar",
        "Murder of Julius Caesar",
        "Killing of Julius Caesar",
        "Stabbing of Julius Caesar",
        "Murder of Caesar",
        "Killing of Caesar",
        "Stabbing of Caesar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Pliny the Younger wrote a letter to Trajan concerning the treatment of these people, the earliest\nreference to these people that wasn’t written by one of them. These people built elaborate catacombs to\nbury their dead and were blamed for a Great Fire by Nero. As a prelude to gladiatorial competitions, these\npeople were forced to fight animals in the arena. For ten points, name these people who were persecuted\nin the Roman Empire for their worship of Jesus.",
      "answer": [
        "Roman Christians",
        "Christians"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "At the end of his life, Marcus Aurelius told those around him “weep not for me; think rather” of those affected by one of these disasters; that disaster began during the reign of Antoninus Pius and is sometimes named after Galen. The port of Piraeus [pi-ray-us] is the estimated starting point of one of these disasters that began in 430 BC in Athens. Under Justinian, over 20 million people were killed in one of these that was caused by Yersinia pestis. Bubonic is a type of, for ten points, what type of widely-spreading disease?",
      "answer": [
        "plagues",
        "Antonine Plague",
        "Plague of Galen",
        "Plague of Athens",
        "Plague of Justinian",
        "bubonic plague"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A leader of this kingdom founded the League of Corinth after crushing the Sacred Band of Thebes at Chaeronea [care-oh-nay-uh]. After a leader of this empire died, its generals feuded in the Wars of the Diadochi [die-ah-doe-kee], which produced the Ptolemaic Kingdom and Seleucid Empire. A leader of this kingdom defeated Darius III at the Battle of Issus before conquering Babylon at the Battle of Gaugamela. For ten points, name this kingdom led by Philip II and Alexander the Great.",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Macedonia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Scipio Aemilianus facilitates dialogue between historical Romans in this author’s On the Commonwealth. This author lays out the foundations for a new Roman constitution is On the Laws, which survives in fragments. After this man’s execution, Fulvia reportedly stabbed his dead tongue with a hairpin to punish him for speaking the Philippics against her husband, Mark Antony. For ten points, name this Roman orator and philosopher who was executed by the Second Triumvirate.",
      "answer": "Marcus Tullius Cicero"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, who shared leadership with Crixus and Oenomaus, routed Mummius when he attacked against orders. Gaius Claudius Glaber tried to starve this man’s forces while they camped on the slopes of Mount Vesuvius. Many of this man’s supporters were crucified by Crassus along the Appian Way after they lost the Third Servile War. For ten points, name this former gladiator who died in 71 BC while leading a slave revolt against the Roman Republic.",
      "answer": "Spartacus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This deity was depicted with horns in many reproductions of statues made during Roman rule, reflecting this god’s conflation with the Egyptian deity Ammon. Libon of Elis designed a Doric temple to house a depiction of this god, which was crafted using ivory and gold plates surrounding a wooden core by Phidias; that statue of this deity at Olympia was one of the Seven Wonders of the Ancient World. For ten points, name this Greek god often depicted in art wielding a thunderbolt.",
      "answer": "Zeus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group was the first target of Justinian’s reconquest wars. These people, along with the Alans, were led by Genseric. These people captured Carthage in 439 AD, making it the capital of their North African empire. Pope Leo I was able to limit, but not stop, these people’s 455 sack of Rome. For ten points, name this Germanic tribe whose name has become synonymous with defacing and destroying property.",
      "answer": "Vandals"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader, who introduced the aureus, is the subject of a lifesize marble sculpture found in Prima Porta in 1863. The Ara Pacis shows this leader in triumphal procession. This leader adopted the title of divi filius after gaining power 17 years after the murder of Julius Caesar. Along with Marc Antony and Lepidus, he formed the Second Triumvirate. For ten points, name this first emperor of Rome.",
      "answer": [
        "Augustus Caesar or Octavian",
        "Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus",
        "Gaius Octavius Thurinus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man began his writing career after facing exile following the fall of Amphipolis. In one work by this man, a winning army’s diplomats state that “the strong do what they can and the weak suffer what they must.” This man’s most famous work includes the Melian Dialogue and recounts how the Delian League was led into war against Sparta. Pericles’ Funeral Oration was recorded by, for ten points, what ancient Greek historian and author of a History of the Peloponnesian War?",
      "answer": "Thucydides"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler repudiated his marriage to Desiderata, the daughter of his rival Desiderius. A biography of this ruler by Einhard relates how he besieged and conquered Pavia, after which he took the title of King of the Lombards. Leo III urged this man to restore his authority from Roman conspirators, leading to his 800 AD coronation. For ten points, name this ruler of the Franks and Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Charlemagne",
        "Charles I",
        "Charles the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "While contesting power over Silk Road cities in the Fergana Valley, this empire defeated the Tang Dynasty at the River Talas. A ruler of this empire gifted Charlemagne both an elephant and a water clock that perplexed his court. This empire, which was later centered in Mamluk Egypt, had its capital sacked in the 13th century by Hulagu Khan. For ten points, name this empire that built Baghdad and succeeded the Umayyads.",
      "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
    },
    {
      "question": "One faction of fans of this sport supposedly promoted the heresy of Monophysitism, opposing pro-Orthodoxy fans. Supporters of this sport burned half of Constantinople during the reign of Justinian the Great in the Nika Revolt. The richest athlete in this sport, Gaius Appuleius Diocles, competed for the Reds using a quadriga. For ten points, name this sport held in the Byzantine Hippodrome and the Roman Circus Maximus, a highly dangerous vehicular race.",
      "answer": "chariot racing ”race” not needed after mentioned"
    },
    {
      "question": "A funerary work from this civilization shows two lovers with braided hair, embracing and smiling. The Sarcophagus of the Spouses was created by people in this civilization, as was the Chimera of Arezzo, which was later owned by the Medici family. This civilization, which was wrongly credited with creating the Capitoline Wolf, produced a statue of Apollo found in its city of Veii. For ten points, name this civilization in ancient Italy whose art influenced that of ancient Rome.",
      "answer": "Etruscans"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this man discovered a plan by King Artag to betray him, he invaded Iberia and captured fortresses like Harmozica and Seusamora. This man was selected to replace Lucius Lucullus in a war against Mithridates VI of Pontus. Ptolemy XIII ordered the execution of this man after Julius Caesar defeated him at the Battle of Pharsalus. For ten points, name this Roman general that led the Optimates faction of the Roman Senate against Julius Caesar’s Populares.",
      "answer": [
        "Gnaeus Pompey Magnus",
        "Pompey the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "By defeating Eugenius at one of these locations in 394, Theodosius I quashed polytheism in favor of Christianity and briefly reunified the Roman Empire. Before a battle at another one of these geographical locations, the winning commander saw the phrase “in hoc signo vinces” in a dream, after which he painted the Chi-Rho [kye-roh] on his soldiers” shields. Constantine I defeated Maxentius in a 312 AD battle at, for ten points, what type of geographical location, an Italian one of which is crossed by the Milvian Bridge?",
      "answer": [
        "rivers",
        "bridge before read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This party twice nominated Charles Pinckney for President, with Pinckney soundly losing both times. During the War of 1812, this party lost much of its public support after renouncing the war at the Hartford Convention. One member of this party wrote the First Report on the Public Credit in his role as the first Secretary of the Treasury. For ten points, name this party supported by Alexander Hamilton, the early rival of the Democratic-Republicans.",
      "answer": "Federalist Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rebellious general established a ruling dynasty in this empire after winning the Battle of Anfao. Ibn al-Mukhtar chronicled the early monarchs of this empire in his Tarikh al-fattash. The Dendi Kingdom formed out of the collapse of this empire. At the Battle of Tondibi, this empire launched a stampede of cattle in a failed attempt to defeat Judar Pasha’s Moroccan forces. Askia Muhammad led, for ten points, what rival of Mali, a West African empire led from Gao?",
      "answer": [
        "Songhai",
        "Songhay"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Prior to this battle, Joachim Murat [yoh-ah-keem mu-rah] was admonished for declaring an armistice at Sch¨ongrabern [SCHUN-grah-bern] without his superior’s consent, giving the enemy time to join forces near Brno [BIR-no]. One general, who sought to begin this battle before the entrance of Prussia into the war, baited Franz von Weyrother’s [VIE-roh-ter’s] forces by abandoning the Pratzen Heights. The Treaty of Pressburg was signed after this battle, dissolving the Holy Roman Empire. For ten points, name this 1805 victory over the Third Coalition by Napoleon.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Austerlitz",
        "Battle of the Three Emperors"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This empire was ruled by the Asen Dynasty which came to power after Ivan Asen won a 7-year siege at Tarnovo. Basil II fought a series of wars against this empire, earning a nickname for slaying its people. A leader of this empire had the Peslav Literary School create the Cyrillic alphabet. Under the leadership of Simeon the Great, this empire fought the Magyars in several wars with neighboring Hungary. For ten points, name this empire that, in 809 AD, took control of Sofia.",
      "answer": "Bulgarian Empire"
    },
    {
      "question": "The fisherman Dictys took in this man and his mother after they were cast to sea in a wooden chest. This man received a magic wallet from Hermes and an invisibility helm from Hades. Grandfather to both Heracles and Helen of Troy, during one quest, this son of Danae stole a shared eye from the Gray Sisters. After killing a sea monster, this hero married Andromeda. For ten points, name this Greek hero who used a reflective shield during his slaying of Medusa.",
      "answer": "Perseus T"
    },
    {
      "question": "This non-Egyptian state was founded by Qutb al-Din Aibak, a Mamluk who succeeded Muhammad of Ghor. The general Zafar Khan established the breakaway Bahmani Sultanate after a revolt against this state. A member of the Tughlaq Dynasty, Muhammad, attempted to shift its capital to the Deccan Plateau. This state was defeated by Babur at the First Battle of Panipat, causing it to be succeeded by the Mughal Empire. For ten points, name this Muslim state that ruled much of India from a namesake city.",
      "answer": "Delhi Sultanate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two answers required: One of these two countries was granted access to the Danube by the other following the Treaty of Edirne. After one of these two countries was victorious at Philippopolis and Shipka Pass, it was able to force the treaty of San Stefano upon the other. France and Britain were drawn into the Crimean War after the navies of these two empires clashed at Sinope. For ten points, Alexander III and Sultan Abdul Hamid II led what two empires that often fought over territory in the Black Sea?",
      "answer": "Russia and the Ottoman Empire both answers required"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man heaped up a funeral pyre of horse saddles on which to immolate himself if he was in danger of being captured at a 451 battle in Gaul. Defeated at that Battle of the Catalaunian Plains by a Roman-Visigoth alliance, he later returned to Italy to renew his marriage claim to Honoria, though he was stopped outside Rome after meeting Pope Leo I. After the death of his brother Bleda, he became king of his people, the Huns. For ten points, name this \"Scourge of God.\"",
      "answer": "Attila the Hun"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city began as a small Akkadian settlement and grew under the Amorite dynasty in the 18th century BC. This city was captured by the Hittites and afterwards the Kassites, who renamed it Karanduniash. Sennacherib [sen-ACK-uh-rib] led a war against this city, whose sixth king established a code of law engraved on a seven foot tall, black stone stele. For ten points, name this city, once the site of the Ishtar Gate, ruled by Esarhaddon, Nabonidus [na-BOH-nih-duss], and Nebuchadnezzar II.",
      "answer": "Babylon T"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man built a line of fortifications around Alesia to defeat Vercingetorix and demanded that his pirate captors ransom him for a higher sum of money. The phrase “the die is cast” was uttered by this lover of Cleopatra before he crossed the Rubicon. This man’s assumption of extraordinary powers was Dopposed by Cassius and Brutus. For ten points, name this member of the First Triumvirate and Roman dictator who was assassinated on the Ides of March.",
      "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jean Gerson helped resolve a crisis in this organization by rejecting two candidates to lead it, while Emperor John VIII joined the Council of Ferrara-Florence to seek the aid of this organization. This organization was based out of Avignon with the support of Philip IV, but it moved back to its original home after the Council of Constance. This organization split with its Eastern counterpart in 1054 after an excommunication from the Ecumenical Patriarch. For ten points, name this organization headed by the Pope in Rome.",
      "answer": "Roman Catholic Church"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Greek loss at this battle led to Boeotia [bee-OH-shuh] being overrun. 700 Thespians and 400 Thebans fought at this battle as part of the losing force. The son of Eurydemus betrayed the Greeks at this battle, but was forced to flee Greece after the Battle of Salamis. That man, Ephialtes, was the reason Themistocles’s defensive plan failed and the Persians were thus able to advance. For ten points, name this batRtle at the Hot Gates where Leonidas and his 300 Spartans attempt to hold off the Persian army.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Thermopylae",
        "Battle of the Hot Gates before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In modern Spain, this general created a makeshift bridge to cross the Baetis [[BAY- tiss]] River to win the Battle of Munda. Tribes like the Bibroci [[bee-BROH-kee]] and the Ancalites united around Cassibelanus [[cah-see-beh-LAH-nus]] in a failed attempt to repel this man's invasion of Britannia. This writer of De Bello Gallico defeated and captured the King Vercingetorix [[ver-sin-GEH-toh-riks]] during the Siege of Alesia. The Rubicon was crossed by, for ten points, what Roman dictator?",
      "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the Bellingham Riots in Washington, over 100 people of this faith were placed into \"protective custody\" by the Asiatic Exclusion League. This faith names an \"Empire\" which formed when various misl [[MEE-suhl]] states united to take advantage of the rapidly deteriorating Mughal [[moo-GAHL]] Empire. Bodyguards of this faith assassinated Indira[[in-DIH-ruh]]GandhifollowingviolenceinthePunjabduringOperation Blue Star. Gobind Singh [[goh-BIHND \"SING\"]] and Guru Nanak led, for ten points, which minority faith of India? ANSWER:Sikhism (orSikhi; acceptSikhs) (6) This one-time stateattorneygeneralarguedinfavorofthedefendantinthecaseVan Ordern v. Perry which concerned a Ten CommandmentsmonumentsattheStateHouse.The Anti-Defamation League censured this politician for comparing mass shootings to the Holocaust after the Sutherland Springs tragedy. This man provoked criticism when he blamed the unimplemented \"Green New Deal\" for his state's power plant failure during a 2021 ice storm. The Texas Heartbeat Act was signed by, for ten points, which Republican governor?",
      "answer": "GregAbbottor Gregory WayneAbbott"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man supposedly diverted an invasion of Britannia to have his army collect seashells along the English Channel. While campaigning with his father, Germanicus, this man earned a nickname related to wearing a child's version of a military outfit. This emperor, who was assassinated by the Praetorian Guard, supposedly tried to make his horse Incitatus [[in-kih-TAH-tuhss]] a Roman consul. For ten points, name this insane successor of Tiberius, whose name translates to \"Little Boot.\"",
      "answer": [
        "Caligula",
        "Gaius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1992, this modern nation invaded its eastern neighbor in an attempt to protect the independence of the region of Nagorno-Karabakh. TalaatPashaorderedforcedmarches through the SyrianDesertbythisnation'snamesakeethnicgroup,killingoveronemillionof them. Multiple wars with Azerbaijan have been fought by, for ten points, what Caucasian nation that faced a 20th century \"Genocide\" under the Ottoman Empire?",
      "answer": [
        "Republic ofArmeniaorHayastani Hanrapetut’yun",
        "acceptArmenian Soviet Socialist Republic",
        "orHaykakanSovetakan Soc'ialistakanHanrapetut'yun",
        "Armenian Genocide"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Along with acting as watchmen, freedmen known as vigiles [[VIH-jih-less]] worked in this profession, often using a substance called acetum [[AH-keh-tum]]. Men in this profession in Ancient Greece used ox intestines as a flexible hose. Thefirstbrigadeofthese people in Rome notoriously refused to do their job untildistressedcitizensnegotiatedwith Crassus over the saleoftheirhomesforminimalprices.Fortenpoints,namethisprofession held by people who put out blazes. ANSWER:Firefighters (acceptFiremen; orFirewomen) (8) This man was given the name \"Big Turtle\" after becoming the adopted son of Chief Blackfish following his capture by the Shawnee. This former Quaker led an expedition to scout the area which became the Wilderness Road. This head of the TransylvaniaCompany founded a namesake \"Borough,\" one of the first colonial settlements west of the Appalachians. The Cumberland Gap was blazed by, for tenpoints,whatpioneerwhosettled modern Kentucky?",
      "answer": "DanielBoone"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's reforms were sabotaged when Qi (pr. CHEE) sent dancing girls and horses to\ndistract the Duke of Lu. This man advocated the \"reification (pr. RAY-iff-uh-CAY-shun) of\nnames\" and the \"five relationships.\" For 10 points, name this author of the \"Five Classics\" whose\nsayings, collected in the Analects, form the basis of a traditional Chinese ruling philosophy.",
        "answer": "Confucius"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Confucius lived during the Spring and Autumn period, in which what Chinese dynasty,\nnominally in power from 1046 to 256 BC, was in decline?",
        "answer": "Eastern Zhou, Zhou, Zhou Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A powerful official in this government was the \"censor,\" who determined eligibility for the\nSenate. Politicians under this government followed the \"cursus honorum\" to move through the\nranks of aedile (pr. EY-dial), quaestor (pr. KWAI-stor), praetor (pr. PRAI-tor), and finally\nbecome one of two consuls. For 10 points, name this governmental system which was replaced\nby the Empire.",
        "answer": "Roman Republic, Republic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A legendary censor was the \"elder\" man of what name, who was also known for ending\nhis speeches in the Senate by declaring \"Carthage must be destroyed?\"",
        "answer": "Cato"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following this battle, Locris and Phocia (pr. FOH-see-uh) \"Medized\" (pr. MEED-eyzd). This\nbattle ended after Ephialtes (pr. eph-FYE-ull-TEEZ) showed the \"goat path\" to the winning\nforce, commanded by Xerxes (pr. ZERK-seez). For 10 points, name this 480 BC battle in which\nLeonidas (pr. LEE-oh-NYE-duss) led three hundred Spartans in holding a pass for three days\nagainst Persia.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Thermopylae",
          "Thermopylae"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Also present at Thermopylae were troops from what city, which used the Sacred Band to\ncome to prominence in the fourth century BC and was the legendary home of Oedipus (pr. ED-uhpuss)?",
        "answer": "Thebes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was targeted by the Unilateral Declaration of Independence, which removed a\ncolony from this empire to protest its plans for racial integration. This empire's leader gave the\nWinds of Change speech as it began to give up control of Ghana, Nigeria, and Rhodesia. For 10\npoints, name this empire which, along with France, was the largest colonizer of Africa.",
        "answer": [
          "British Empire",
          "British",
          "UK",
          "United Kingdom",
          "Great Britain",
          "Britain"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rhodesia later was renamed as which African country with its capital at the city of\nHarare (pr. huh-RAH-ray)?",
        "answer": "Zimbabwe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was attacked by Croesus (pr. CREE-sus) of Lydia after the Delphic Oracle said\nthat \"a great empire will fall.\" This empire relied on local satraps who were loyal to emperors\nsitting at Susa. For 10 points, name this empire founded by Cyrus the Great, which launched a\nnamesake series of wars on Greece at the start of the fifth century BC.",
        "answer": [
          "Persian Empire",
          "Persia",
          "Achaemenid Empire",
          "Achaemenid"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Persian Emperor lost at Issus and Gaugamela, and was the third to hold this\nname?",
        "answer": "Darius"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This system was restored following the overthrow of Hippias (pr. HIP-ee-uss), after which its\ncentral feature was the boulé (pr. BOO-lay). This system involved citizens being arranged into\ndemes (pr. DEEMZ) by Cleisthenes (pr. CLICE-thuh-neez). For 10 points, identify this\npolitical system used in classical Athens, which inspired similar vote-based systems in the\nmodern world.",
        "answer": [
          "Athenian democracy",
          "democracy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Members of the boulé were selected by what method, also used to pick the tenth of an\narmy that Romans \"decimated\" and the date of the massacre of Jews in the Book of Esther?",
        "answer": [
          "by drawing of lots",
          "lots"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This party effectively ceased to function after the failure of Rufus King's Presidential\ncampaign. They were discredited when members were accused of using blue lights to signal to\nBritish ships during the War of 1812, and by their organization of the secessionist Hartford\nConvention. For 10 points, name this party of DeWitt Clinton, Alexander Hamilton, and John\nAdams.",
        "answer": [
          "Federalist Party",
          "Federalists"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What name is given to the period of political unity under James Monroe, in which\nnearly no opposition to the Democratic-Republican Party existed?",
        "answer": "Era of Good Feelings"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The informer \"Stakeknife\" infiltrated this organization, which began the \"Long War\" in the\nearly 1970s. This group claimed responsibility for killing MP Airey Neave as well as the 1984\nBrighton hotel bombing which nearly killed Margaret Thatcher. For 10 points, name this militant\nCatholic group which advocated transferring Northern Ireland away from the United Kingdom.",
        "answer": [
          "IRA",
          "Irish Republican Army",
          "Provisional IRA",
          "Provisional Irish Republican Army"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which 1972 massacre of Irish demonstrators by UK paratroopers shares its name with\na 1905 killing spree in St. Petersburg?",
        "answer": "Bloody Sunday"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nicholas Reeves has controversially suggested using radar in this location to find hidden rooms. Pierre\nLacau supervised a study of this location funded by Lord Carnavon who died of mosquito-borne disease\nshortly after it was opened. This location, officially designated KV62, was discovered in 1922 by Howard\nCarter. For ten points, name this surprisingly well-preserved burial site of a boy pharaoh.",
        "answer": [
          "the tomb of King Tutankhamun",
          "tomb Tut",
          "Crypt Tut",
          "Burial site Tut",
          "Tomb of Tutankhamun"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "King Tut’s tomb, like numerous other pharaoh tombs, was discovered in this Egyptian valley\nacross the Nile River from Thebes.",
        "answer": [
          "Valley of the Kings",
          "Kings"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man noted that “Our constitution does not copy the laws of neighboring states” in a speech\nthat offered “comfort [...], not condolence” after the first year of the Archidamian War. He evacuated the\nfarmers of Attica to within the Long Walls, which protected them from Spartan skirmishes but led to the\nspread of plague that killed him. For ten points, name this statesman of the Athenian Golden Age who\nopposed Sparta in the early Peloponnesian War.",
        "answer": "Pericles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pericles’ 431 BC oration commemorating the first year of the Peloponnesian War was given at\nwhat type of event?",
        "answer": "funeral"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Abd al-Karim al-Nahlawi led a coup against this President which resulted in the collapse of the\nUnited Arab Republic. In 1952 this man and Muhammed Naguib ousted King Farouk as members of the\nFree Officers Movement. In 1956, this co-founder of the Non-Aligned Movement nationalized the Suez\nCanal. For ten points, name this second President of Egypt, serving between Naguib and Anwar Sadat.",
        "answer": [
          "Gamal Abdel Nasser",
          "Nasser"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lake Nasser was created when what structure was built on the Nile River?",
        "answer": [
          "Aswan High Dam",
          "Aswan Dam"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a drunken brawl, this man killed his officer Cleitus the Black, who had earlier saved this\nman’s life during the Battle of the Granicus River. This man’s successors were known as the Diadochi\n[dee-AH-doh-kee], and this rider of Bucephalus defeated Darius III at the Battle of Gaugamela. For ten\npoints, name this son of Phillip II, a king of Macedon who conquered Persia.",
        "answer": "Alexander the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alexander the Great was tutored as a youth by this man, who established the Lyceum and wrote\nNicomachean Ethics.",
        "answer": "Aristotle"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This position was ended by the Peace of Pressburg, which also created the Confederation of the\nRhine. One holder of this position stood in the snow outside Canossa to do penance, and the successor to\nthis position was decided by the prince-electors. These men were crowned by popes until 1530, and the\nphrase “sacrum” was added to this title by a man who fought the Lombard League. For ten points, name\nthis position, which was held by Charles V and Frederick Barbarossa.",
        "answer": [
          "Holy Roman Emperor",
          "Romisch-deutscher Kaiser",
          "Romanorum Imperator"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 1356 decree known by this color was issued by Charles IV to set the number of electors to\nselect the Holy Roman Emperor at seven.",
        "answer": [
          "Golden Bull of 1356",
          "Gold",
          "Bulla Aurea"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Senussi opposed French influence on this continent in the early 20th century. The Battle of\nGazala was fought near a northern port on this continent, Tobruk, during the Western Desert Campaign;\nthat campaign culminated in the Second Battle of El Alamein, where Erwin Rommel’s forces were forced\nto retreat to this continent’s northernmost country, Tunisia. For ten points, name this continent where an\nAllied World War 2 campaign pushed the Germans out of Libyan and Egyptian deserts.",
        "answer": "Africa"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Erwin Rommel was known as the “Desert” one of these crafty animals.",
        "answer": [
          "Desert Fox",
          "Fox"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These entities were controlled through “ingenuity” among other things, utilizing both a mahout and\na howdah. Among the most famous use of this weapon was at the Battle of the Hydaspes River by King\nPorus against Alexander the Great. Hannibal baffled the Romans by crossing the Alps with them. For ten\npoints, name this animal, akin to an ancient tank, which is now hunted for its ivory tusks.",
        "answer": [
          "elephants"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alexander’s victory over King Porus at the Hydaspes required one of these military maneuvers,\nalso performed by Julius Caesar - albeit with no immediate enemy - at the Rubicon.",
        "answer": [
          "river crossing",
          "river cross"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This kingdom defeated King Zwide [zwee-day] by dividing his army at the Mhlatuze [m-hlah-TOOzay] River. Mpande ruled this kingdom after surviving Dingane’s purges; Mpande’s son, Cetshwayo\n[keht-SHWAH-yoh], led this empire to an early victory at Isandlwana [ee-son-dull-WAH-nah] over the\nBritish before losing its capital, Ulundi, in 1879. For ten points, name this south African kingdom, led in\nthe early 19th century by Shaka.",
        "answer": [
          "Zulu",
          "Zulu Kingdom",
          "Zulu Empire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shaka developed the iklwa [ee-kull-wah], an improvement over the assegai, which was a thrown\nversion of this weapon. Greek hoplites carried a type of these called sarissae, which were often 20 feet long.",
        "answer": "spear"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Supposedly, prior to this battle, Cyrsillus and his wife were stoned for suggesting surrender. Washed\nup sailors were slaughtered on Psyttaleia [sit-uh-LYE-uh] by Aristides [air-uh-STY-dees], and a throne\nwas erected for the losing commander to watch the battle. This battle vindicated the “wooden walls”\nof Themistocles, who advocated abandoning Athens prior to this battle. The battles of Artemisium and\nThermopylae were fought prior to, for ten points, what naval battle, a victory for the allied Greeks over\nXerxes I?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Salamis",
          "Salamis"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One commander under Xerxes was Queen Artemisia of this place, which was also the birthplace\nof Herodotus and the site of a notable mausoleum.",
        "answer": "Halicarnassus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s head was immersed in a jar of blood by Queen Tomyris to satisfy his bloodlust. This\nmonarch used camels to win the Battle of Thymbra, defeating Croesus of Lydia. His capture of Babylon\nis detailed in his namesake Cylinder, and Isaiah refers to him as a messiah for his freeing the Jews from\nthe Babylonian Captivity. The satrapy system was created by, for ten points, what first Achaemenid ruler\nof the Persian empire?",
        "answer": [
          "Cyrus the Great",
          "Cyrus II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Aside from the Cylinder, most of what is known of Cyrus’ reign comes from what “father of\nhistory,” who traced the origins of the Greco-Persian War in his Histories?",
        "answer": "Herodotus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler was forced to retreat through the Derbend Pass after his invasion of Sassanid Persia. This\nman’s uncle Ruga united his people, then was succeeded by this man and his brother, Bleda. Aetius was\nforced to ally with Theodoric in order to defeat this ruler, who may have begun an invasion after Honoria\nsent him a ring. According to legend, this ruler died of a nosebleed. For ten points, name this “Scourge of\nGod” who attempted to sack Rome as the leader of the Huns.",
        "answer": [
          "Attila",
          "Attila the Hun"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Upon invading Italy, Attila was confronted by Leo I, a holder of this religious position, outside Rome.",
        "answer": "Pope"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was divided into themes, which each supplied a portion of troops, until they were\nsupplemented by the tagmata system. The Latin Empire occupied the lands of this empire until the\nPalaiologos dynasty reclaimed the land. The Fourth Crusade ended in the sacking of this empire, whose\nEcumenical Patriarch served as religious head of this country’s Orthodox faith. For ten points, name this\nsuccessor state of the Roman Empire that was based in Constantinople until 1453.",
        "answer": [
          "Byzantine Empire",
          "Byzantine",
          "Eastern Roman Empire",
          "Eastern Roman"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Byzantine Empire’s navy used this incendiary weapon. Its recipe is lost, but it was notable\nfor being able to burn on water.",
        "answer": "Greek fire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was ruled by dual kings from the Agiad and Eurypontid dynasties, who were responsible to\nthe ephors. One ruler of this city, Lycurgus the Lawgiver, introduced the agoge [ah-goh-gah], a rigorous\ntraining program for all young men. One king of this city replied “come and take them” after being asked\nto lay down his arms by Xerxes I. Leonidas died at Thermopylae with 300 soldiers from, for ten points,\nwhat militaristic Greek city-state, a rival of Athens?",
        "answer": "Sparta"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Spartan farms were primarily worked by these slaves, who were primarily conquered Messalians.",
        "answer": "helots"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s ruins held the Plimpton 322 tablet, which lists a series of Pythagorean triples. A 7th\nand 6th century BC empire based in this city grew under Nabopolassar and ended when Nabondius was\ndefeated by Cyrus the Great. The Hittites defeated an older empire in this city, which instituted a law\ncode based on the “eye for an eye” concept. For ten points, name this Mesopotamian city-state led in\ndifferent millennia by Hammurabi and Nebuchadnezzar, who built the Hanging Gardens there.",
        "answer": [
          "Babylon",
          "Neo-Babylonian Empire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "These Mesopotamian step-pyramids had shrines at their highest levels. Nabonidus rebuilt a\nGreat one of these in Ur.",
        "answer": "ziggurats"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this empire, people or land could be granted a form of quasi-sovereignty called immediacy. In 1500,\nthis empire was reformed into a series of six Circles, including the Swabian Circle. This empire’s rulers\nincluded Henry IV, who feuded with Gregory VII during the Investiture Controversy, and a ruler who\ndefeated the Magyars at Lechfeld. Otto the Great led, for ten points, what patchwork of states located in\nmodern-day Germany, whose emperor was crowned by the Pope in Rome?",
        "answer": [
          "Holy Roman Empire",
          "Holy Roman",
          "HRE"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Holy Roman Emperor tried to subjugate the Italian states before drowning in the Saleph\nRiver during the Third Crusade.",
        "answer": [
          "Frederick Barbarossa",
          "Barbarossa",
          "Frederick I"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man authorized military intervention against Samos after Miletus asked for aid in a war for the city of Priene. This man secured power over his rivals, Cimon and Thucydides, through ostracism. This man described the greatness of his city in a celebrated funeral oration and hired Iktinos and Kallikrates to renovate the Acropolis. For ten points, name this leader of the Delian League and statesman of Athens during its Golden Age.",
        "answer": "Pericles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pericles controversially ordered the Delian League to stop accepting military support as dues and to take this financial action, making it easier for Pericles to renovate the Acropolis. Description acceptable.",
        "answer": [
          "moving the treasury to Athens leniently",
          "word forms and phrasings",
          "also",
          "mention of storing the money in the Parthenon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Friar Diego Dur´an helped document the history of this civilization. In this empire’s capital, many invaders drowned while carrying gold during an attack by Eagle Warriors. A man who helped conquer this empire betrayed Diego Velasquez and was aided by La Malinche [mah-lin-chay]. Montezuma II ruled, for ten points, what empire that was conquered after Hern´an Cort´es arrived in Tenochtitlan in modern-day Mexico?",
        "answer": "Aztec Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Aztec Empire is known as this type of alliance, based on the number of city-states involved. In the 19th century, a South American war pitted Paraguay against an alliance of this type.",
        "answer": [
          "Triple Alliance",
          "descriptive answers relating to 3 allies"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These units fought with allied cavalry that were organized into alae. These army units were divided into smaller units called maniples and organized into three layers based on experience. After twenty five years of service in one of these units, a veteran was granted citizenship. Each possessed an eagle standard and they were organized into ten separate cohorts, each commanded by a centurion. Thousands of men fought in, for ten points, what largest unit of the Roman army?",
        "answer": "legion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Entry requirements to the legions were relaxed by this Roman general, a six-time consul and uncle of Julius Caesar. Legionnaires were nicknamed his mules because of the heavy packs he made them wear.",
        "answer": "Gaius Marius"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This building was damaged in 1687 was damaged by the Morosini explosion when Venetian shelling destroyed an ammo dump inside. In 1809, statues from the Erechtheum [erek-thee-um], Propylaea [pro-puh-LIE-uh], and this building were removed with the permission of the Ottoman Empire by the Earl of Elgin. Forty-six inner columns and 23 outer columns surround the exterior of this building. For ten points, name this landmark Greek temple dedicated to Athena in Athens.",
        "answer": "the Parthenon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Parthenon, as well as the Erechtheum and Propylaea, stands in this hilltop area in Athens.",
        "answer": "the Acropolis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire’s first ruler abdicated his throne to fight for his daughter’s claim to another throne in the Liberal Wars. This empire fought the Cisplatine War over the status of the Banda Oriental [or-ee-en-TALL], and it decisively defeated Francisco Solano Lopez in the War of the Triple Alliance. Princess Isabel signed the Golden Law to abolish slavery in this empire. Dom Pedro I founded, for ten points, what empire that gained its independence from Portugal and became the largest South American country?",
        "answer": "Empire of Brazil"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dom Pedro I founded the empire after he declared “Independence or Death” in a “Cry” made at what namesake river?",
        "answer": [
          "Ipiranga River or Brook, etc.",
          "Cry of Ipiranga"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This material was used to make the death mask of Agamemnon, which Heinrich Schliemann found in 1876. This material, which is heavily used in cloaks in a painting of two lovers on a cliff by Gustav Klimt, was used with ivory to create chryselephantine sculptures. The outermost funerary mask of King Tutankhamen was plated in this material, whose “leaf” is often used in art. Alchemists often sought to create, for ten points, what metal that makes up electrum coins with silver?",
        "answer": "gold"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Heinrich Schliemann found the mask of Agamemnon while excavating this ancient Greek archaeological site. This site south of Corinth names an era of Greek history.",
        "answer": [
          "Mycenae",
          "word forms, like Mycenaean Era"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While this man was busy subduing Parthia, his wife Fulvia used the issue of disputed land grants to fight a rival in the Perusine War. After this politician was denounced by fourteen speeches known as the Philippics, he condemned their author to death. His power was effectively ended after a devastating loss to Agrippa in the Battle of Actium. For ten points, name this ally and friend of Julius Caesar who committed suicide after mistakenly thinking that his lover, Cleopatra, was already dead.",
        "answer": "Marc Antony or Marcus Antonius"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This orator and consul of Rome attacked Marc Antony in the Philippics.",
        "answer": "Marcus Tullius Cicero"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire captured the city of Karansebes after the Austrian army attacked itself and killed over 1,000 soldiers. This empire offered support to the Crimean Khanate, leading to the burning of Moscow in 1571. This empire faced the Celali Revolts, several uprisings of irregular musketeers and Janissaries during the 16th century. Following the Great Northern War, this empire offered refuge for Charles XII of Sweden. For ten points, name this empire that reached its peak under Suleiman the Magnificent.",
        "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1529, Suleiman laid siege to this European city, but ultimately failed. The Ottomans tried again in 1683, but were decisively defeated by the Hapsburgs and the Holy League.",
        "answer": "Vienna"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1815, Henry Salt hired Giovanni Belzoni to secure a giant statue of this man, the Younger Memnon, from his memorial temple. This ruler ordered the creation of a temple complex at Abu Simbel, partially to honor his wife Nefertari. With Mursili III, this man signed the Eternal Treaty which was meant to end his conflict with the Hittites. For ten points, name this Egyptian pharaoh who won the Battle of Kadesh in 1259 BC.",
        "answer": [
          "Ramses II",
          "Ramses the Great"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Kadesh may have been the largest clash of these vehicles in history.",
        "answer": "chariots"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This government was opposed by the Organisation Consul, which was formed by participants in the failed Kapp Putsch and members of the Freikorps. After an attack allegedly carried out by Marinus van der Lubbe, this government limited civil liberties with the Fire Decree. The constitution of this government was amended by the Enabling Act of 1933, in which Paul von Hindenburg granted his chancellor extreme political power. Massive hyperinflation afflicted, for ten points, what post-World War I German government?",
        "answer": "Weimar Republic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marinus van der Lubbe was accused of setting fire to this German parliament building in Berlin.",
        "answer": [
          "Reichstag",
          "Reichstagsgebaude"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The losers of this battle suffered from Quintus Dellius defecting and giving their battle plans to the enemy. The smaller and quicker Liburnian ships fought against a smaller force of quinqueremes near the Ambracian Gulf in this battle. The victory of Marcus Agrippa at this battle allowed a leader to take the title “Princeps” and usher in the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this 31 BC naval battle in which Augustus defeated Marc Antony and his Egyptian allies.",
        "answer": "Battle of Actium"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marc Antony was supported by this ruler of Egypt who, after the battle, legendarily killed herself with an asp bite.",
        "answer": "Cleopatra VII Philopator"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Martin Garcia Onez de Loyola led an expedition to capture the last emperor of these people, Tupac Amaru. Legendarily, a ruler of this empire came out of Pacaritambo holding a golden staff after being birthed from the divine pairing of Mama Killa and Inti. This empire that used the knot system of quipu experienced a civil war between Huascar and Atahualpa. For ten points, name this South American empire conquered by the conquistador Francisco Pizarro.",
        "answer": "Incan Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This capital city of the Incan Empire is home to the Coricancha temple. Pachacuti built the empire from this city.",
        "answer": "Cuzco"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When syncretized with the Egyptian god Amun, this Roman deity was depicted with ram horns. The Flamen Dialis was the high priest of this deity, who formed the Archaic Triad with Quirinus and Mars. In the Metamorphoses, this deity transforms into an eagle to kidnap the Phrygian prince Ganymede; in the form of a bull, this god kidnapped Europa. This son of Saturn was the husband of Juno and the father of Minerva. For ten points, name this chief Roman god, the Roman equivalent of Zeus.",
        "answer": [
          "Jupiter",
          "Jove"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Metamorphoses was written by this Roman poet, who was exiled to the Black Sea city of Tomis by Augustus Caesar in 8 AD.",
        "answer": "Ovid or Publius Ovidius Naso"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle took place on a plain where the invading army attacked on the advice of the exiled Athenian tyrant Hippias. Prior to this battle, a request for aid was sent to Sparta, but due to the Carneia festival, the Spartans did not arrive until after this battle was over. In this battle, one thousand hoplites from Plataea reinforced the Athenians who were led by ten generals including Miltiades. For ten points, name this battle that thereafter named a distance race, the same length as the route run by the messenger Pheidippides. R",
        "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Persian king during the Battle of Marathon was this man, the third King of Kings of the Achaemenid Empire and the father of Xerxes the Great.",
        "answer": [
          "Darius I",
          "Darius the Great"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "With a name from the Greek for “able to choose,” one of these groups called the Lollards was created by John Wycliffe. A campaign led by Simon de Montfort targeted one of these groups in Toulouse, D while another of these groups formed defensive squares with their wagons in battle. Examples of these groups include the Hussites, who were condemned at the Council of Constance, and the Cathars, who were attacked during the Albigensian Crusade. For ten points, name these historical groups that were persecuted for rejecting core Catholic beliefs.",
        "answer": [
          "Heretics",
          "word forms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hussites were based in Bohemia, the site of which is now found in what modern nation?",
        "answer": "Czech Republic"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was stabbed to death after he had used the nickname \"Priapus\" to mock Cassius Chaerea. After abandoning his invasion of Britain, this man allegedly ordered his troops to collect seashells on the shores of Gaul as \"spoils of the sea.\" While traveling as a child with his father Germanicus, this emperor, whose birth name was Gaius, gained the nickname \"little boot.\" For ten points, name this Roman emperor who succeeded Tiberius and allegedly made his horse a consul.",
        "answer": [
          "Caligula",
          "Gaius before it is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Caligula was only 28 years old when he was assassinated by this elite Roman army unit, the personal bodyguards of the Emperor.",
        "answer": "Praetorian Guard"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man began one war after raiding the Temple of Vesta and revealing his rival’s plans to have his sons control the empire. This founder of the Urban Cohorts constructed the Ara Pacis [PAH-chees] to celebrate the peaceful era of the Pax Romana. That era began after this man’s commander Marcus Agrippa was victorious over his rival, Marc Antony, at the battle of Actium. For ten points, name this adoptive son of Julius Caesar who became the first Roman emperor. R",
        "answer": [
          "Augustus Caesar",
          "Octavian",
          "Gaius Octavius"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This title, often given to the Pope and coming from the Latin for “bridge builder,” was taken by Augustus as the head of the Roman religion.",
        "answer": [
          "Pontiff",
          "Pontifex Maximus"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these groups named Hispana vanishes from history around 120 AD and is known as the \"lost\" one of these groups. Marius made these groups permanent standing bodies and professionalized their subcommanders, the centurions. These groups each consisted of over 5000 infantry members and 120 foreign auxilia cavalry during the height of the Empire, at which time there were as many as thirty of them. For ten points, name these highest-level divisions of the Roman army.",
        "answer": [
          "Roman Legions",
          "Legio",
          "or Legiones"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 17th and 18th legions, which were commanded by Mark Antony, were disbanded after what 31 BC naval victory that secured hegemony for Augustus?",
        "answer": "Battle of Actium"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the aftermath of a revolt by this figure, the freedman Polyclitus [[pah-lee-KLY-tuss]] led an investigation that deposed governor Gaius Suetonius Paulinus [[\"GUY\"-us swee-TOH-nee-us paw-\"LIE\"-nuss]]. This woman's husband, Prasutagus [[prah-soo-TAY-gus]], originally submitted to vassal status duringtheconquestsofClaudius. With the Trinovantes [[trih-noh-VAN-teez]], this woman's combined tribal army burned down bothEboracum[[eh-BOR-sh-kum]]andLondinium.Fortenpoints,namethisqueenof the Iceni [[\"eye\"-SEE-nee]] tribe who led Britons in a 1st century revolt against the Roman Empire. ANSWER:Boudicca(acceptBuddug; acceptBoadicea)) BONUS: Boudicca's Revolt occurred during the reign of this Julio-Claudian Roman emperor who built theDomus Aurea. ANSWER:NeroClaudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus (7) The White Army-aligned Alasha Orda controlled this modernnation'sareaforthree years before surrendering to the USSR. The Soviet Space Program launched the Vostok missions from this country's Baikonur [[BYE-koh-noor]] Cosmodrome. The Russian-led Commonwealth of Independent States was established by an agreement signed in this nation known as the AlmatyProtocol.NursultanNazarbayev[[nah-zar-BYE-eff]]onceruled, for ten points, what former Soviet republic in Central Asia?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic ofKazakhstan orQazaqstan Respublikasy",
          "acceptKazakhSoviet Socialist Republic",
          "orQazaqKeńestik Sosıalıstik"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before being exiled to Mexico, this rival of Stalin and reformer of the Red Army spent much of 1928 in exile in Kazakhstan.",
        "answer": [
          "LeonTrotsky",
          "Lev DavidovichBronstein"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "FAMOUS GREEKS",
      "prompt": "What person or god from ancient Greece...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of the Olympian gods and was depicted in a famous statue at Olympia?",
          "answer": "Zeus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ran naked through the streets of Syracuse shouting \"Eureka\" after discovering buoyancy?",
          "answer": "Archimedes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led a cult which opposed eating beans and discovered a side length theorem for right\ntriangles?",
          "answer": "Pythagoras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the \"gadfly of Athens\" whose Apology was recorded by Plato?",
          "answer": "Socrates"
        },
        {
          "question": "Offered a salt spring as a gift to Athens, which then chose Athena as its patron deity instead?",
          "answer": "Poseidon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote the first book of history, The Persian Wars?",
          "answer": "Herodotus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was called the \"tenth muse\" for her accomplishments as a female poet on Lesbos?",
          "answer": "Sappho"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave a \"funeral oration\" on Athenian ideals during the Peloponnesian War?",
          "answer": "Pericles"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MEDIEVAL EASTERN EUROPE",
      "prompt": "In the Middle Ages, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire which, by the 1070s, was reduced to the area around Constantinople?",
          "answer": "Byzantine, Byzantine Empire, Eastern Roman Empire, Eastern Roman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country first organized by the Piast Dynasty, which was later invaded by its neighbor\nGermany to start World War II?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim empire based in Turkey which conquered much of the region from 1308 to 1571?",
          "answer": "Ottoman, Ottoman Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country where the Grand Duchy of Muscovy formed around the city of Moscow?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group which briefly overran Eastern Europe after defeating the Hungarians at Mohi in 1241?",
          "answer": "Mongol, Mongols"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Vladimir the Great converted a namesake state to Christianity before it became the\nUkrainian capital?",
          "answer": "Kiev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince of Wallachia (pr. wah-LAY-kee-uh) whose practice of putting opposing soldiers on\nstakes inspired vampire legends?",
          "answer": "Vlad the Impaler, Vlad Dracula, Dracula, Vlad III, Vlad Tepes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle, which shares its name with a Balkan country that declared independence in 2008 from\nSerbia?",
          "answer": "Kosovo"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THIRTY YEARS WAR",
      "prompt": "During the Thirty Years War, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Increasingly chaotic German “empire” whose member states took opposing sides?",
          "answer": [
            "Holy Roman Empire",
            "Holy Roman",
            "Hapsburg Empire",
            "Hapsburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Major world religion whose Protestant Reformation was one of the war’s ultimate causes?",
          "answer": "Christianity"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty which formally ended the conflict?",
          "answer": [
            "Peace of Westphalia",
            "Westphalia",
            "Munster",
            "Osnabruck",
            "Treaty of Westphalia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Activity which peaked during the war, and used the Malleus Mallificarum to determine whom to\nburn?",
          "answer": [
            "witch-hunts",
            "witch",
            "witch-hunting"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose pragmatic policy was made by Cardinal Richelieu (pr. ree-shell-OO)?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Event in which two diplomats were thrown out a window that sparked the fighting?",
          "answer": "Defenestration of Prague"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Sweden who was killed at the Battle of Lutzen?",
          "answer": [
            "Gustavus Adolphus",
            "Gustav II",
            "Gustav Adolf"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Watershed historical year in which it ended?",
          "answer": "1648"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ANCIENT INDIA",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nirvana-focused religion founded by Siddhartha Gautama?",
          "answer": [
            "Buddhism",
            "Buddhist"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Language ancestral to modern Hindi that was used to write ancient Hindu texts?",
          "answer": "Sanskrit"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number first articulated in fifth-century India during the invention of decimals?",
          "answer": [
            "zero",
            "shunya"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "River at which Indian civilization grew near the city of Varanasi?",
          "answer": "Ganges"
        },
        {
          "question": "Macedonian general who reached the borders of India with his conquests?",
          "answer": [
            "Alexander the Great",
            "Alexander"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Treatise on the art of love composed around the second century AD?",
          "answer": [
            "Kama Sutra",
            "Kamasutra"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Epic about the king of Ayodha (pr. eye-OH-duh) defeating the demon Ravana?",
          "answer": "the Ramayana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty in power from 322 to 185 BC, whose emperors included Asoka (pr. uh-SHOWkuh)?",
          "answer": [
            "Mauryan dynasty",
            "Maurya",
            "Mauryan empire"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In classical India, what was the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "CLEOPATRA",
      "prompt": "Cleopatra VII was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The last Macedonian pharaoh of what land prior to its conquest by Rome?",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "The mother of a child whose father was what Ides of March assassination victim?",
          "answer": [
            "Julius Caesar",
            "Caesar",
            "Gaius Julius Caesar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Later the partner of what Second Triumvirate member who fought with Octavian?",
          "answer": [
            "Mark Antony",
            "Marcus Antonius",
            "Antony",
            "Antonius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The daughter, sister, and mother of men with what dynastic name?",
          "answer": "Ptolemy"
        },
        {
          "question": "The loser of what 31 BC naval battle which sealed her fate?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Actium",
            "Actium"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Killed, in some versions, when she allowed what kind of snake to bite her?",
          "answer": "asp"
        },
        {
          "question": "Presented to her first Roman lover inside what object?",
          "answer": [
            "rolled-up carpet",
            "rug"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Able to fulfill a vow to serve a ten-million-sesterces dinner by serving what item dissolved in\nvinegar?",
          "answer": [
            "pearls"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "OTTOMAN GROUPS",
      "prompt": "What group within the Ottoman Empire was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The ethnicity of the ruling class?",
          "answer": [
            "Turks",
            "Turkish"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Allowed to maintain the Church of the Holy Sepulchre in Jerusalem and placed under the\n\"protection\" of the Russian tsar?",
          "answer": [
            "Christians"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Elite soldiers who were massacred in the Auspicious Incident?",
          "answer": "Janissaries"
        },
        {
          "question": "The section of the sultan's palace where his wives and concubines lived, or, by extension, that\ngroup of women themselves?",
          "answer": "harem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led in a namesake \"revolt\" by Faisal (FAI-sul) and T.E. Lawrence?",
          "answer": [
            "Arabs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Increased in number following their expulsion from Spain, and able to compose the Shulchan\nAruch (SHOOL-kahn aa-ROOK) legal code in Damascus?",
          "answer": [
            "Jews"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The profession of forty percent of the empire's subjects, who had to pay taxes in kind?",
          "answer": [
            "farmers",
            "farming",
            "agriculture"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The ethnicity which went to war against the Ottomans for a final time under Abbas I?",
          "answer": [
            "Persians",
            "Iranians"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EASTERN EUROPEAN COUNTRIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Unified the cities of Buda and Pest in 1873?",
          "answer": "Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was in a union with Montenegro until 2006?",
          "answer": "Serbia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Broke away from the Czech Republic in 1993?",
          "answer": "Slovakia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had 7 border guards killed in a Soviet assault near Vilnius?",
          "answer": "Lithuania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to electrician, politician, and Nobel Peace Prize winner Lech Walesa [vah-WE-sa]?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the modern site of the former capital of the Kievan Rus?",
          "answer": "Ukraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saw its leader, Nicolae Ceausescu [CHO-ses-koo], executed for war crimes in a 1989 revolution?",
          "answer": "Romania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was considered the “last dictatorship in Europe” under Alexander Lukashenko?",
          "answer": "Belarus"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which Eastern European country..."
    },
    {
      "category": "MESOPOTAMIA",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Means “land between the rivers” in what ancient language spoken in Corinth and Athens?",
          "answer": [
            "Ancient Greek",
            "Greek"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the birthplace of what practice, including irrigation, that allowed hunter-gatherers to settle?",
          "answer": [
            "agriculture",
            "farm",
            "farming"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was home to the Hanging Gardens in what city?",
          "answer": "Babylon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Used what wedge-shaped form of writing?",
          "answer": "cuneiform"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the eastern part of a region known by what two-word term, named for its shape and arable land?",
          "answer": "Fertile Crescent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was located between what two rivers that flow to the Persian Gulf?",
          "answer": [
            "Tigris and Euphrates Rivers",
            "Tigris and Euphrates"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was primarily located in what modern-day country, whose cities include Mosul and Basra?",
          "answer": "Iraq"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was home to what city, whose Great Ziggurat was excavated by Leonard Woolley?",
          "answer": "Ur"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Mesopotamia..."
    },
    {
      "category": "NORTH AFRICAN CITIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The capital of Libya, where Muammar Gaddafi ruled until 2011?",
          "answer": "Tripoli"
        },
        {
          "question": "The largest city in Morocco and setting of a classic 1943 film?",
          "answer": "Casablanca"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of a U.S. Embassy in Libya that was attacked on September 11, 2012?",
          "answer": "Benghazi"
        },
        {
          "question": "The former Phoenician colony whose earth was supposedly salted in 146 BCE?",
          "answer": "Carthage"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city in central Mali home to the Sankore Madrassa, popularly believed to be hard to reach?",
          "answer": "Timbuktu"
        },
        {
          "question": "The home of the Great Library, a Wonder of the Ancient World?",
          "answer": "Alexandria"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of a 1956 general strike and bombings of a milk bar and other French civilian targets by the\nFLN?",
          "answer": "Algiers"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of an Egyptian battle that Winston Churchill called “perhaps the end of the beginning?”",
          "answer": "El Alamein"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which North African city is or was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "BYZANTINE EMPIRE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Its capital city, originally known as Byzantium and now known as Istanbul?",
          "answer": "Constantinople"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Italian city whose empire it continued in the east?",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "The empire that arose after conquering the Byzantine Empire, which lasted until World War 1?",
          "answer": [
            "Ottoman Empire",
            "Ottoman"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The official monotheistic religion of the empire, after a decree by Theodosius?",
          "answer": [
            "Christianity",
            "Orthodox Christianity"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The religious images banned by Leo III in the 8th century?",
          "answer": [
            "Icons",
            "Iconoclasm"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Germanic tribe conquered by Belisarius in north Africa, whose name now refers to general destruction\nof property?",
          "answer": [
            "Vandals",
            "vandalism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The wife of Justinian who convinced him not to flee from the Nika Riots?",
          "answer": "Theodora"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Ottoman sultan who conquered Constantinople in 1453, ending the Byzantine Empire?",
          "answer": [
            "Mehmed II",
            "Mehmed the Conqueror"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In the history of the Byzantine Empire, who or what was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "ANCIENT GREEK WARFARE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The Greek god of war?",
          "answer": "Ares"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city in Asia Minor legendarily sacked by Greek troops after the abduction of Helen?",
          "answer": "Troy"
        },
        {
          "question": "The militaristic rival of Athens led by Leonidas?",
          "answer": "Sparta"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Boetian city represented by the Sacred Band?",
          "answer": "Thebes"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city that dominated the isthmus connecting the Peloponnese to mainland Greece and was the\ncenter of a League led by Philip II?",
          "answer": "Corinth"
        },
        {
          "question": "The battle formation of rows of spear-bearing hoplites whose name comes from the Greek for\n“fingers”?",
          "answer": "Phalanx"
        },
        {
          "question": "The wooden ships with three banks of oars that formed the “Wooden Wall” of Athens?",
          "answer": [
            "Triremes"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The 479 BCE land battle where the Greeks killed the Persian general Mardonius?",
          "answer": "Plataea"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In Ancient Greece, who or what was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "AUGUSTUS CAESAR",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the first holder of what position, after Rome had spent centuries as a republic?",
          "answer": [
            "Emperor of Rome",
            "Emperor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was known by what birth name prior to taking that position?",
          "answer": [
            "Gaius Octavian",
            "Octavian",
            "Gaius Octavius",
            "Octavius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a member of what political alliance with Marcus Lepidus and Marc Antony?",
          "answer": "Second Triumvirate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Won the Battle of Philippi against what partner of Cassius?",
          "answer": [
            "Marcus Junius Brutus",
            "Brutus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cried out for Varus to give him back what units, a standard military division in Rome?",
          "answer": "legions"
        },
        {
          "question": "Personally owned what region south of the Mediterranean, the source of much of Rome’s grain?",
          "answer": [
            "Egypt",
            "Aegyptus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Held what other title, which translates to “first citizen?”",
          "answer": [
            "Princeps civitatis",
            "Princeps"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Relied on what trusted admiral and son-in-law who commissioned the Pantheon?",
          "answer": [
            "Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa",
            "Agrippa"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Augustus Caesar..."
    },
    {
      "category": "The Silk Road",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire that traded with China along the Silk Road, delivering coins and medallions depicting Maximian and Marcus Aurelius.",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Empire",
            "Rome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Animals found on mulberry trees, from which silk was produced in ancient China.",
          "answer": "silkworms"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire whose Royal Road, established by Darius the Great, formed part of the Silk Road.",
          "answer": "Persian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity that names the southern branch of the road and whose Oolong and Darjeeling varieties were traded along it.",
          "answer": [
            "tea",
            "Oolong tea",
            "Darjeeling tea"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where the Karakoram Highway follows the Silk Road to Abottabad, just west of Islamabad.",
          "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian peninsula whose Silla and Goguryeo kingdoms benefited from trade along the road.",
          "answer": "Korean Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inns along the Silk Road, named for the groups of travelers who would rest there.",
          "answer": "caravanserai or caravansara"
        },
        {
          "question": "Christian sect that rejected Mary as being the mother of god and spread to China via the Silk Road.",
          "answer": [
            "Nestorian Christianity",
            "Nestorianism and other word forms"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "WATER",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Michigan city that has lacked safe tap water since 2014.",
          "answer": "Flint"
        },
        {
          "question": "Water delivery structures, such as the Pont du Gard and one in Segovia, built by the Romans.",
          "answer": "aqueducts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where the Turpan oasis provides water to Uyghurs [wee-gurs] in Xinjiang [shin-jiang]\nProvince.",
          "answer": [
            "People’s Republic of China",
            "China"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancient Greek inventor of a water-lifting screw and, supposedly, a death ray.",
          "answer": [
            "Archimedes of Syracuse",
            "Archimedes"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of underground water source, like the Ogallala, that are threatened by over-irrigation.",
          "answer": "aquifers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea that has largely dried up since the Amu Darya and Syr Darya were diverted for irrigation by the\nSoviets.",
          "answer": [
            "Aral Sea",
            "Aral"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Southeast Asian empire that built barays to store water near Angkor Wat.",
          "answer": [
            "Khmer Empire",
            "Khmer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Abbasid caliph who built a qanat for water in Mecca, as well as the House of Wisdom in Baghdad.",
          "answer": [
            "Harun al-Rashid",
            "al-Rashid"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "ANCIENT EGYPT",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Common title used by Egyptian monarchs, such as the ruler of Egypt in the Book of Exodus.",
          "answer": "Pharaoh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Writing system of Ancient Egypt that preceded the development of demotic script.",
          "answer": [
            "Hieroglyphs",
            "Hieroglyphics"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Slab, discovered in 1799, whose three writings allowed the Egyptian writing system to be deciphered\nfrom Greek.",
          "answer": "Rosetta Stone"
        },
        {
          "question": "Boy king whose tomb was unearthed by Howard Carter in 1922.",
          "answer": [
            "King Tutankhamun",
            "King Tut",
            "Tut",
            "Tutankhamun"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mythical creature with a human’s head and a lion’s body that is depicted in a massive sculpture in\nGiza.",
          "answer": "Sphinx"
        },
        {
          "question": "First of the three “Kingdom” periods, which encompasses the Third through the Sixth Dynasties.",
          "answer": [
            "Old Kingdom",
            "Old"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Animal that alternatively names Faiyum and Sumenu, two centers of worship for the deity Sobek.",
          "answer": [
            "crocodile",
            "Crocodilopolis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Foreign people who, centuries before the Sea Peoples attacked, invaded Egypt to establish the\nFifteenth Dynasty and ruled from Avaris.",
          "answer": "Hyksos"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "The KGB",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nation whose main intelligence agency was the KGB from 1954 to 1991.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "USSR",
            "CCCP",
            "SSSR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Current world leader who once served as a KGB agent.",
          "answer": "Vladimir Putin"
        },
        {
          "question": "American counterpart of the KGB whose leaders have included Allen Dulles.",
          "answer": "Central Intelligence Agency or CIA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where the KGB could not control Kabul or defeat the mujahideen during a 1980s war.",
          "answer": "Islamic Republic of Afghanistan"
        },
        {
          "question": "European country where Imre Nagy’s [im-reh nazh’s] 1956 revolt was violently crushed by the KGB.",
          "answer": "Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "KGB chairman from 1967 to 1982 who briefly succeeded Leonid Brezhnev as a world leader.",
          "answer": "Yuri Andropov"
        },
        {
          "question": "British spy ring, including Kim Philby, who passed confidential information to the KGB during the 1940s and 50s.",
          "answer": [
            "Cambridge Five",
            "Cambridge Four",
            "Cambridge Spy Ring, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Building formerly used as KGB headquarters and which once notoriously housed political prisoners on the ground floor.",
          "answer": "Lubyanka Gandhi Political Power If an answer in this round is a person with the last name Gandhi, give their full first name. You will not"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Roman Gladiators",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Amphitheater in Rome where the largest gladiatorial games were held.",
          "answer": "Colosseum or the Flavian Amphitheater"
        },
        {
          "question": "Horse-drawn vehicles that served as a platform for some gladiators.",
          "answer": "chariots"
        },
        {
          "question": "Social class for many gladiators, especially foreign ones captured as spoils of war.",
          "answer": "slaves or servus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Symbol given by spectators to determine whether the winner of a fight should kill or spare the loser.",
          "answer": [
            "a turned thumb or pollice verso",
            "anything related to turning your thumb a certain way"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of gladiatorial combat done in a naumachia [now-mock-ee-uh].",
          "answer": [
            "naval battle",
            "anything to do with ships, boats, the sea, filling the Colosseum with water, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Special weapon used by the lightly-armored retiarius against secutores. Either of two English answers is acceptable.",
          "answer": "net and/or trident"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gladiator-related business operated by lanistas.",
          "answer": [
            "training schools",
            "ludus",
            "ludi"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mesopotamia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern capital of Iraq where artifacts were damaged in the Gulf Wars.",
          "answer": "Baghdad"
        },
        {
          "question": "World wonder built in Babylon by Nebuchadnezzar for his homesick wife.",
          "answer": "Hanging Gardens of Babylon"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Fertile” shape of the Mesopotamian region where early civilization grew.",
          "answer": "Fertile Crescent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Important river that meets the Euphrates [yoo-fray-teez] at the Shatt al-Arab in southern Iraq.",
          "answer": "Tigris River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Writing style developed in Mesopotamia, using a stylus to make wedge shapes on tablets.",
          "answer": "cuneiform"
        },
        {
          "question": "7th century BC Neo-Assyrian ruler who collected 30,000 of those tablets in a library now held in Britain.",
          "answer": "Ashurbanipal"
        },
        {
          "question": "First urban civilization in Mesopotamia, led during the Uruk Dynasty by Gilgamesh.",
          "answer": "Sumerians"
        },
        {
          "question": "First ruler of Akkad, a “Great” ruler who once served as cupbearer.",
          "answer": "Sargon the Great or Sargon I"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Babylon",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Region, whose name is Greek for “land between the rivers,” where Babylon grew.",
          "answer": "Mesopotamia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Process of providing a controlled flow of water that was used in Babylonian agriculture.",
          "answer": [
            "irrigation",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Wonder of the Ancient World built in Babylon by Nebuchadnezzar for his homesick wife.",
          "answer": "Hanging Gardens of Babylon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Babylonian king whose law code allowed for balanced retribution, usually described as “eye for an eye.”",
          "answer": "Hammurabi"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Great” king who founded the Persian Empire and conquered the Neo-Babylonians in the 6th century BC.",
          "answer": "Cyrus the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "Babylonian goddess of love, known as the Queen of Heaven, who names a gate now housed in Berlin.",
          "answer": [
            "Ishtar Gate",
            "Inanna"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Assyrian king who destroyed Babylon in 689 BC and was assassinated eight years later.",
          "answer": "Sennacherib"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire, founded by Sargon the Great, that originally built the city of Babylon.",
          "answer": "Akkadian Empire"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Greco-Persian Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Battle, whose name means “Fiery gates,” where a Persian force slaughtered 300 troops in a mountain pass.",
          "answer": "Battle of Thermopylae"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek city-state, a rival of Athens, that sent those 300 troops under King Leonidas.",
          "answer": "Sparta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek victory during the first Persian invasion, after which Phidippides legendarily ran over 25 miles to Athens.",
          "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pivotal naval battle of the second Persian invasion that took place in a narrow strait outside Athens.",
          "answer": "Battle of Salamis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Persian king, the son of Darius, who watched that naval battle from a throne on a cliff.",
          "answer": "Xerxes the Great or Xerxes I"
        },
        {
          "question": "BC.",
          "answer": "Themistocles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Uprising among Greek cities on the coast of Anatolia that Athens supported, provoking the first Persian invasion",
          "answer": "Ionian Revolt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek queen of a city-state in modern Turkey who led a fleet in the aforementioned naval battle.",
          "answer": "Artemisia of Halicarnassus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Considering the first century BC wars in Gaul, name the...",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about Considering the first century BC wars in Gaul, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country south of Belgium that was the site of the wars.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "River that marked the border of Gaul, and later, the Roman Empire.",
          "answer": "Rhine River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mountain range that separated Gaul into Cis and Trans provinces before its conquest.",
          "answer": [
            "Alps",
            "Cisalpine and/or Transalpine Gaul"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman general who recorded his conquest of Gaul in Commentaries.",
          "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arverni general who led a major uprising against Roman rule, marked by a victory at the Battle of Gergovia.",
          "answer": "Vercingetorix"
        },
        {
          "question": "City surrounded by two walls by the Romans in 52 BC, marking one end of the Gallic resistance.",
          "answer": "Alesia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman legion that was “mounted” by its commander during the war.",
          "answer": "Tenth Legion or Legio X Equestris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conference that continued the Gallic Wars and gave Crassus command in Syria.",
          "answer": "Lucca Conference"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mughal Empire",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Mughal Empire, a descendant of Tamerlane.",
          "answer": "Babur"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mausoleum built by Shah Jahan for his wife, Mumtaz.",
          "answer": "Taj Mahal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battlesite where, in 1526, that first emperor defeated Ibrahim Lodi, the last Sultan of Delhi.",
          "answer": "First Battle of Panipat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chair of the Mughal Emperors, which was carried off to Persia after Nader Shah’s sack of Delhi.",
          "answer": "Peacock Throne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military building in Delhi built by the Mughals, named for its distinctive color.",
          "answer": "Red Fort"
        },
        {
          "question": "Syncretic faith founded by the third Mughal emperor in 1582.",
          "answer": "Din-i-Illahi"
        },
        {
          "question": "1739 victory for Nader Shah against the Mughal emperor Muhammad Shah that opened the way for his sack of Delhi.",
          "answer": "Battle of Karnal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire led by Sher Shah that conquered much of Northern India during the reign of Humayun.",
          "answer": "Suri Empire"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Alexander the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Kingdom he ruled in northern Greece.",
          "answer": "Macedonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Previous king, his father, who was assassinated in 336 BC.",
          "answer": "Philip II of Macedon"
        },
        {
          "question": "City, destroyed by Mount Vesuvius, where a mosaic of him was found.",
          "answer": "Pompeii"
        },
        {
          "question": "333 BC battle where he defeated Darius III, two years before Darius” ultimate defeat at Gaugamela.",
          "answer": "Battle of Issus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Beloved horse who he supposedly tamed by hiding his shadow.",
          "answer": "Bucephalus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle where that horse died near a namesake river in India.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Hydaspes River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Phoenician island city where he constructed a causeway to allow an attack.",
          "answer": "Tyre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Collective name for his generals, who fought several wars to divide his empire.",
          "answer": "Diadochi"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Black Death",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Disease caused by Yersinia pestis that is blamed for the Black Death.",
          "answer": "Bubonic plague or black plague"
        },
        {
          "question": "Animals that spread the disease while being attached to black rats.",
          "answer": "fleas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancient trade route between China and Europe that helped spread the disease.",
          "answer": "Silk Road or Silk Route"
        },
        {
          "question": "Occupation that dealt with the plague while wearing a heavy overcoat and a beak mask.",
          "answer": "plague doctors"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nomadic ethnic group originating in northern India that was blamed for the outbreak and discriminated against.",
          "answer": [
            "Romani people",
            "gypsy, but inform the players that it’s considered a pejorative term"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire, led by Jani Beg, that may have started the outbreak by launching corpses into Kaffa.",
          "answer": [
            "Mongol Empire",
            "Golden Horde"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Survey ordered by William the Conqueror that gives the closest pre-Black Death population of England.",
          "answer": "Domesday Book"
        },
        {
          "question": "1351 law created by Edward III to address the labor shortage caused by the plague.",
          "answer": "Statute of Laborers"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Six Day War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Egyptian peninsula on the Red Sea captured by Israel along with Gaza.",
          "answer": "Sinai Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian leader, an advocate of Pan-Arabism who nationalized the Suez Canal.",
          "answer": "Gamal Abdel Nasser"
        },
        {
          "question": "One eyed Israeli Minister of Defense who oversaw the capture of East Jerusalem.",
          "answer": "Moshe Dayan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Waterway that provided Israel’s only access to the Red Sea; its closure by Egypt sparked the war.",
          "answer": "Straits of Tiran"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sudanese capital city where a namesake resolution that vowed continued belligerency with Israel was passed.",
          "answer": "Khartoum"
        },
        {
          "question": "American spy ship accidentally targeted by an Israeli airstrike.",
          "answer": "USS Liberty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Israeli general and future prime minister, victor of the decisive Battle of Abu Ageila against Egyptian forces.",
          "answer": "Ariel Sharon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Preemptive Israeli airstrike against the Egyptian Air Force that began the conflict.",
          "answer": "Operation Focus IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Coup d’etats",
      "prompt": "Name the nation from a description of the coup...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "In 1999, Nawaz Sharif was overthrown by General Pervez Musharraf. F",
          "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1992, Carlos Andres Perez held power against a coup led by Hugo Chavez.",
          "answer": "Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela"
        },
        {
          "question": "The 23-F incident in 1981 was squelched by King Juan Carlos.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Spain A"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1940, after the German invasion, a coup attempt was made by Vidkun Quisling.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Norway"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Sergeants’ Revolt of 1933 propelled Fulgencio Batista to power.",
          "answer": "Republic of Cuba"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1953, U.S. and British intelligence overthrew Mohammed Mosaddegh.",
          "answer": "Imperial State of Iran R"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1970, Prince Sihanouk was overthrown by Prime Minister Lon Nol.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Cambodia"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1971, Milton Obote was overthrown by army chief Idi Amin.",
          "answer": "Republic of Uganda D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Rosetta Stone",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Pictographic system of Egyptian writing that was the third language written on the Stone F",
          "answer": "hieroglyphics"
        },
        {
          "question": "First language on the Stone, common in the Hellenistic world",
          "answer": "Ancient Greek"
        },
        {
          "question": "French general who discovered the Stone while invading Egypt",
          "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current site of the Stone in London",
          "answer": "British Museum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Script on the middle portion of the Stone, commonly used in Egyptian administrative documents",
          "answer": "Demotic"
        },
        {
          "question": "French scholar who successfully deciphered the third language on the Stone in 1822",
          "answer": "Jean-Francois Champollion R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Family of the Egyptian ruler who issued the proclamation written on the Stone",
          "answer": "Ptolemies or Ptolemaic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Document that ceded the Stone to British control in 1801, the Capitulation of this city",
          "answer": "Alexandria D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Kingdom of Rome...",
      "prompt": "Name the the kingdom of rome......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was started by this mythical founder who killed his brother Remus F",
          "answer": "Romulus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Built this central plaza of Rome, the center of discussion and public life",
          "answer": "Roman Forum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Started on this first of the Seven Hills of Rome",
          "answer": "Palatine Hill A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Relied on this order of priestesses to tend the sacred fire",
          "answer": [
            "Vestal Virgins",
            "Vestals"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Had kings who wore the Toga Picta of this royal color",
          "answer": "Purple"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was ruled by two kings of this name, the younger of whom was overthrown after the rape of Lucretia",
          "answer": "Tarquinius R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Apocryphally abducted the women of this nearby tribe as seen in a famous Rubens painting",
          "answer": "Sabines"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was overthrown after this man led a revolution and became co-consul with Collatinus.",
          "answer": "Lucius Junius Brutus D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Banana Republics",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Author of \"The Gift of the Magi\" who coined the term \"Banana Republic.\"",
          "answer": "O.Henryor William SydneyPorter"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose Tegucigalpa-based government was overthrown on behalf of the Cuyamel [[KYE-ah-mel]] Fruit Company.",
          "answer": "Republic ofHondurasRepública deHonduras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chilean poet and senator who criticized banana republics as exploitative in his book Canto General[[heh-neh-RAHL]].",
          "answer": "PabloNerudaor Ricardo Eliécer NeftalíReyesBasoalto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Guatemalan president who instituted anti-big business land reforms, leading to his overthrow by CIA-backed soldiers.",
          "answer": "JacoboÁrbenzJuan JacoboÁrbenzGuzmán 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "October Revolution",
      "prompt": "Concerning the October Revolution, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Soviet Union who led the Bolsheviks during the revolution.",
          "answer": "Vladimir IlychLeninor Vladimir IlyichUlyanov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trudovik president of the Provisional Government and leader of the prior February Revolution.",
          "answer": "AlexanderKerenskyor Alexander FyodorovichKerensky"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. journalist buried in the Kremlin who recounted events inTen Days that Shook the World.",
          "answer": "John \"Jack\"Reedor John \"Jack\" SilasReed 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Reign of Augustus",
      "prompt": "Concerning the reign of the first Roman emperor, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Rival and loyal general to Julius Caesar whom Augustus defeated at the naval Battle of Actium.",
          "answer": [
            "MarkAntony",
            "MarcusAntonius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Losing commander at the Battle of Teutoburg Forest whose ghost was supposedly asked to \"give [him] back [his] legions.\"",
          "answer": "Publius QuinctiliusVarus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Right-hand man who commanded his armies in the Wars of the Second Triumvirate.",
          "answer": "Marcus VipsaniusAgrippa 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Renaissance Florence",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Renaissance in Florence, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Political scientist and writer of The Prince who was tortured and exiled from Florence.",
          "answer": "Niccolò Machiavelli or Niccolò di Bernardo dei Machiavelli"
        },
        {
          "question": "Banking family, with members like Cosimo and Lorenzo, who ruled Florence.",
          "answer": "de' Medici or House of Medici"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region in which Florence is located, named for an Italian people of antiquity.",
          "answer": "Tuscany or Toscana"
        },
        {
          "question": "11th century dogmatic split which the 15th century Council of Florence aimed to mend.",
          "answer": "Great Schism or Schism of 1054"
        },
        {
          "question": "Large-scale burning of fine arts and other objects considered lewd by the followers of Savonarola [[sah-voh-nah-ROH-lah]].",
          "answer": "Bonfire of the Vanities or Falò delle vanità"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sculptor who won a competition to design the title fixture for the Florence Cathedral's dome.",
          "answer": [
            "Filippo Brunelleschi ]",
            "Pippo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolt of 14th century wool workers which nearly toppled the sitting government.",
          "answer": "Ciompi ] Revolt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rival republic on the Arno which was sold to Florence by the Visconti family in 1406.",
          "answer": "Republic of Pisa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Naval Affairs in Antiquity",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Naval battle which ended Xerxes's invasion of Greece in 480 BC.",
          "answer": "Battle ofSalamis]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom in modern Somalia that heavily traded with its northwestern neighbor, Egypt.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom ofPuntorPwenet",
            "Land ofPunt 2021-22 C Set History"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mali Empire",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Mali Empire, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Mansawho devalued the price of gold in Cairodue to his generosity.",
          "answer": "MansaMusaI"
        },
        {
          "question": "14th century Moroccan traveler who detoured hishajjto spend eight months in the Mali Empire.",
          "answer": "IbnBattuta"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Charlemagne",
      "prompt": "Concerning the rule and legacy of Charlemagne [[SHAR-luh-MANE]], name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Title he took following his crowning by the Pope, later used by medieval rulers of Germany.",
          "answer": [
            "HolyRoman EmperororEmperorof theRomans",
            "alternate answers likeEmperorofRome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "843 treaty which split his realm between his grandsons.",
          "answer": "Treaty ofVerdun] 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The latest date for this facility's destruction is 642, according to the story blaming Amr ibn\nal As, though it is also believed that Theophilus ordered it (20 pts) ",
        "burned in 391 or that it fell\nvictim to the chaos of the Zenobia revolt. This building housed thousands of (10 pts) ",
        "scrolls and\ntablets and was the jewel of a complex dedicated to the Muses by Ptolemy (pr. TAH-luh-mee).\nFor 10 points, name this center of learning in the Classical world, which was found in Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": "Library of Alexandria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In an 1890 treaty, this empire abandoned its interest in Zanzibar in exchange for an\noddly shaped territory that granted it access to the Zambezi River, known as the Caprivi\nStrip. This empire perpetrated the Herero genocide in what is now (20 pts) ",
        "Namibia. It had to\ngive up what are now Tanzania and Cameroon following its defeat in (10 pts) ",
        "World War I. For\n10 points, name this European-based empire, which was originally constructed by Otto von\nBismarck."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "German Empire",
        "German"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Fossils of this species were first found in the Engis Caves of Belgium, though they get\ntheir name from subsequent finds on the outskirts of Dusseldorf in a namesake (20 pts) ",
        "valley.\nThis species was once believed to have been rendered extinct by bands of rock-throwing\npredators, though it is now known from DNA markers that they (10 pts) ",
        "interbred with the\nancestors of modern humans. For 10 points, name this large-skulled hominid which survived in\nEurope until 40,000 BC."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Neanderthals"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This emperor was the ultimate victor of the Battle of Muhlberg, which suppressed the\nSchmalkaldic (pr. shmal-CALL-dik) League that opposed him. This man's 1525 victory at (20 pts) ",
        "Pavia included the capture of Francis I of France. This father of Philip II summoned (10 pts) ",
        "Martin Luther to the Diet of Worms (pr. VURMZ). For 10 points, name this Hapsburg who\nbriefly united the thrones of Spain and the Holy Roman Empire."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles V",
        "Charles I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A road extending from Castrum Truentinum to the Aurelian Walls of Rome was named\nfor this substance, whose transportation was the impetus for building some of the oldest\nknown (20 pts) ",
        "roads. This substance was traded to the north in exchange for gold from the (10 pts) ",
        "African interior, especially by the Ghana empire. For 10 points, identify this formerly valuable\nsubstance which can now be easily retrieved from natural sources such as seawater and is often\niodized."
      ],
      "answer": "salt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2003, this person was identified as the \"Younger Queen\" mummy by the minority\nfaction of archaeologists which holds that she was the same person as the pharaoh (20 pts) ",
        "Smenkhkare. Berlin's Neues (NOY-iss) Museum currently holds a famous (10 pts) ",
        "bust of this\nperson, which is traditionally attributed to a sculptor known as Thutmose. For 10 points, name\nthis wife of Akhenaten who might have preceded Tutankhamun as pharaoh of Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": "Nefertiti"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city’s empire defeated Ercole d’Este to conquer Commachio and defeated a rival in\nthe War of Chioggia. It was targeted by the League of (20 pts) ",
        "Cambrai, founded by its nemesis\nJulius II. Its Arsenale was said to be able to produce one (10 pts) ",
        "warship a day. A fleet from this\ncity was led by Enrico Dandolo in the Fourth Crusade and sacked Constantinople. For ten points, name\nthis “Most Serene Republic” which was ruled by doges."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Most Serene Republic of Venice",
        "Venice"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) According to Tarikh al-Sudan, this empire’s last ruler was Mahmud IV, whose\ndefeat at the Battle of Djenne caused its collapse. The ton-tigi, or “quiver-masters,”\nadvised this empire’s rulers at its (20 pts) ",
        "Gbara legislature. Its constitution, the\nKouroukan Fouga, was established after its first ruler won the Battle of Kirina. This\nempire’s most famous ruler (10 pts) ",
        "caused inflation by spending tons of gold on his way to Mecca.\nFor ten points, name this West African empire led by Sundieta Keita and Mansa Musa."
      ],
      "answer": "Mali Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man is depicted with his wife in the Coregency Stela. Burnaburiash asked\nthis man for gold and Tushratta wished him well in a set of correspondences named\nfor this man’s capital, (20 pts) ",
        "Amarna. This founder of a (10 pts) ",
        "monotheistic religion changed\nhis name to honor the new god. Nefertiti was the wife of, for ten points, what Egyptian ruler once\nknown as Amenhotep IV who began a monotheistic religion centered on the sun-disk, Aten?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Akhenaten",
        "Napkhuria"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Right before the end of this conflict, action in the Battle of 73 Easting continued\nat Norfolk, and Frederick Franks lost almost no troops while demolishing the (20 pts) ",
        "Republican Guard in this war. It began over disputes about the Rumaila oil field.\nChuck Horner commanded troops in this war before the arrival of (10 pts) ",
        "Norman\nSchwarzkopf. For ten points, name this war in which Operation Desert Storm reacted to Saddam\nHussein’s invasion of Kuwait."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Persian Gulf War",
        "Gulf War",
        "First Gulf War",
        "First Iraq War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An inflammatory letter by Leo of Ohrid helped spark this event. The Council of\nFerrara-Florence tried to reverse this event after John VIII Palaiologos needed help against\nthe (20 pts) ",
        "Ottoman Empire. The Massacre of the Latins worsened the effects of this event\nand led to the Sack of Thessalonica in revenge. The Norman conquest of southern Italy led\nto a call for help that began this event. This event began when a delegation refused to grant\nCerularius the title of (10 pts) ",
        "Ecumenical Patriarch, which resulted in a mutual excommunication. For\nten points, name this split between Roman Catholicism and the Eastern Orthodox church."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Great Schism",
        "Schism of 1054"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city is home to the Erechtheion, a temple probably designed by Mnesicles [neh-sihklees] and financially supported by the treasury of the (20 pts) ",
        "Delian League, which was based\nin this city. This city was connected to its port, several kilometers away at Piraeus, by the\nLong Walls, which were ordered destroyed in (10 pts) ",
        "404 BC after this city lost the Peloponnesian\nWar. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state where Pericles ordered the building of the\nParthenon on the Acropolis."
      ],
      "answer": "Athens"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The eunuch Pothinus tried to depose this ruler with help from Ptolemy XIII. This\nruler’s sister, Arsinoe IV, was killed in the Temple of Ephesus for being a perceived threat.\nThis ruler was legendarily (20 pts) ",
        "smuggled into a room in a rolled up carpet. Her children\nwere given significant land in the Donation of (10 pts) ",
        "Alexandria three years before she fled from the\nBattle of Actium, leading to her lover’s defeat by Augustus Caesar for control of the Roman Empire. For\nten points, name this lover of Mark Antony, the last pharaoh of an independent Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cleopatra VII Philopator",
        "Cleopatra"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One structure on this island was built slightly north of the Stanegate and was near the\nMilitary Way. Julius Caesar made note of the (20 pts) ",
        "chariots used on this island during his\n55 BC invasion. Gaius Suetonius won the Battle of Watling Street on this island to defeat a\nrevolt of the Iceni led by (10 pts) ",
        "Boudicca. One structure on this island was built near Pictland as the\nnorthern border of the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this island, the site of Hadrian’s Wall and a\nRoman province with capital at Londinium, now known as London."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Britannia",
        "Britain",
        "British Isles",
        "British"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s forces were betrayed on a journey to Messina by his hired Cilician pirates;\nshortly after, he was denied a truce, then decisively beaten and killed at the Siler (20 pts) ",
        "River.\nA single man volunteered to lead an army to defeat this former murmillo; the practice of\nkilling every tenth soldier, or decimation, was reintroduced for discipline purposes by that\nvolunteer, (10 pts) ",
        "Crassus. After this leader lost the Third Servile War, his followers were crucified along\nthe Appian Way. For ten points, name this first century BC Greek soldier who led a failed slave revolt\nafter escaping captivity as a Roman gladiator."
      ],
      "answer": "Spartacus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Prior to this battle, the winning commander sent Sicinnus to the opposing camp to fake\ntreason, drawing their forces into an arm of the Saronic Gulf. The losing commander at this\nbattle lamented “my (20 pts) ",
        "men have turned into women, my women men,” after he observed\nArtemisia of Halicarnassus ramming her own ally to escape. Athens was (10 pts) ",
        "abandoned prior\nto this battle, which vindicated the “wooden wall” navy built by Themistocles. For ten points, name this\n480 BC naval battle in which Xerxes’ Persian navy was crushed by a Greek alliance."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Salamis",
        "Salamis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Europa Universalis 4, this empire may choose to lose 100 military power in exchange\nfor a 10 percent national manpower modifier when utilizing the Devshirme system. In the\nTotal War franchise, this empire’s (20 pts) ",
        "Nizam i-Cedit soldiers are named for its real-life\nmilitary reforms carried out by Selim III. In Civilization 5, this empire’s naval maintenance\ncosts are reduced by 67 percent due to the (10 pts) ",
        "“Barbary Corsairs” skill, and it can recruit Sipahi\nhorseman and Janissary units. For ten points, name this empire represented in numerous video games by\nSuleiman the Magnificent."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ottoman Empire",
        "Ottoman"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group bombed the fishing boat of Lord Mountbatten and pushed for the “five\ndemands” during a hunger strike led by Bobby Sands. In 1984, it planted a bomb in the\nGrand Hotel in (20 pts) ",
        "Brighton in a failed assassination attempt on Margaret Thatcher,\nbut it agreed to a cease fire in 1997 after its affiliated political party was allowed into the\nnegotiations for the (10 pts) ",
        "Good Friday agreement. Sinn F´ein was associated with, for ten points, what\nparamilitary group at the forefront of “the Troubles” that fought for an independent Ireland?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Provisional Irish Republican Army",
        "PIRA",
        "IRA",
        "Irish Republican Army"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these structures had its outer layer of tura limestone appropriated for nearby\nconstruction projects, leading it to be nicknamed after its red color. The first of these\nstructures was constructed at Saqqara and consisted of six (20 pts) ",
        "mastabas of differing sizes.\nA bent example of these structures was constructed on the orders of Sneferu. The only (10 pts) ",
        "remaining example of the Seven Wonders of the Ancient World is an example of, for ten points, what\nmassive Egyptian structures that cover royal tombs?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "pyramids",
        "Red Pyramid",
        "Bat Pyramid",
        "Step Pyramid",
        "Bent Pyramid"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Emperor Gallienus slaughtered a force of these people at Naissus in 269 AD. A century\nlater, a group of these people led by Fritigern slaughtered the Romans and killed Emperor\nValens in the Battle of (20 pts) ",
        "Adrianople. This ethnic group’s 3rd century AD appearance\nin the frontiers of Europe hastened the fall of Rome. (10 pts) ",
        "Alaric and Theoderic were among the\nleaders of, for ten points, what Germanic ethnic group that was split into western and eastern branches\nprefixed by “Visi-” and “Ostro-?”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Goths",
        "Visigoths",
        "Ostrogoths"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This city formed a treaty of alliance with Jerusalem in the Pactum Warmundi.\nPope Julius II tried to subdue this city by allying with France and the Holy Roman\nEmpire in the League of (20 pts) ",
        "Cambrai. Zara and Constantinople were sacked by\nsoldiers during the Fourth Crusade in exchange for ships from this city’s ruler, (10 pts) ",
        "Enrico Dandolo. Doges [doh-zhes] ruled, for ten points, what Italian city-state, a rival of Genoa\nknown for its empire on the Adriatic and its system of canals?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Most Serene Republic of Venice",
        "Venice"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this battle, the brother of Aeschylus [ess-kuh-luss] was cut down while attempting to pull a ship to shore by hand. Datis and Artaphernes were aided in this battle by a vengeful (20 pts)",
        "Hippias, who had been exiled earlier by the winning side. Callimachus cast the deciding vote in favor of launching this battle, which resulted in a rout of (10 pts)",
        "Darius’ men. Athens was victorious over Persia in, for ten points, what 490 BC battle that inspires the name of a lengthy footrace?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this conflict, a navy delayed their retreat because of a lunar eclipse; that decision by Nicias doomed the entire force. After Callicratidas lost at this war’s Battle of Arginusae [ar-jin-oo-say], (20 pts)",
        "Lysander retook command and won at Aegospotami. Alcibiades [al- si-BYE-uh-dees] defected from one side in this war shortly before the disastrous Sicilian Expedition, then later re-defected to (10 pts)",
        "Athens. Thucydides wrote a History of, for ten points, what 5th century BC war that Athens lost to Sparta, named for a Greek peninsula?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Peloponnesian War",
        "Sicilian Expedition until “Callicratidas” is read, then prompt on it until it is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ancient culture on this island included the worship of a woman holding two serpents in her hands, “the snake goddess,” and its art used the Horns of Consecration motif in honor of a sacred bull. In the second millennium BC, the (20 pts)",
        "Thera eruption on Santorini devastated this island to the south; that event and a possible Mycenaean invasion from the mainland may have ended a civilization centered on this island that used the still-undeciphered (10 pts)",
        "Linear A script and had its capital at Knossos. For ten points, name this largest Greek island, the home of the Minoan civilization."
      ],
      "answer": "Crete"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Magonid and Barcid families dominated this city-state, which was not allowed to declare war on Masinissa of Numidia according to a treaty that they defied in 149 BC. The Fabian strategy of delaying was used to fight this city-state, which (20 pts)",
        "“must be destroyed” according to the closing statements of Cato the Elder’s speeches. The Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Cannae was won by this city’s most famous general, who crossed the Alps with elephants. For ten points, name this African city-state whose army was led by Hannibal Barca in the Punic Wars against Rome."
      ],
      "answer": "Carthage"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Production of this foodstuff requires nixtamalization [nish-tamal-ization], a soak-and-boil process using a very alkaline solution, to allow it to release nutrients and be more easily digested. That process was developed around 1500 BC and creates (20 pts)",
        "hominy, which can be ground into masa flour and dough. This grain was first domesticated in (10 pts)",
        "southern Mexico and, with beans and squash, was one of the Three Sisters of Native American agriculture. For ten points, name this grain crop that is also known as maize."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "corn",
        "any type of corn",
        "hominy and/or masa before they are mentioned",
        "maize before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Celeres served as the bodyguard of these people. One of these people was chosen to rule after lightning was seen around his head; his Servian Reforms allowed plebeians voting rights. The (20 pts)",
        "Vestal Virgins were brought out of Alba Longa by the second of these people, Numa Pompilius. The first of these people (10 pts)",
        "abducted the Sabine women, founded a city on the Palatine Hill, and may have killed his brother Remus. Lucius Tarquinius Superbus was the last man to hold, for ten points, what position as leader of an ancient city, first held by Romulus?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kings of Rome",
        "Rex"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Richard of Cornwall and Alfonso X of Castile vied to be leaders of this empire in its interregnum. A leader of this empire expanded into Italy by beating Berengar II and defeated Magyar forces at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Lechfeld. Rules for electing rulers of this empire were decided in the 1356 Golden Bull. Gregory VII excommunicated a ruler of this empire, Henry IV, during the Lay Investiture Controversy. (10 pts)",
        "Charlemagne was the first emperor of, for ten points, what European entity largely centered on medieval Germany and Northern Italy?"
      ],
      "answer": "Holy Roman Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Joseph de Guignes believed these people were descended from the Xiongnu [zong-nu]. The Peace of Anatolius and the Treaty of Margus were signed to stop this group’s expansion. (20 pts)",
        "Theodoric and Flavius Aetius fought this group after it had been ruled by men like Rugila and Bleda. These people lost the Battle of the (10 pts)",
        "Catalaunian Plains under a leader who was persuaded not to sack Rome by Pope Leo I. For ten points, name this nomadic group that helped cause the downfall of the Roman Empire under its leader, Attila."
      ],
      "answer": "Huns"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event took place because its country’s “spiritual health and character were both ruined,” according to “The Two Thousand Words,” a controversial essay by Ludvik Vaculik. This event included an (20 pts)",
        "Action Programme that emphasized freedom of speech against outdated Communist policies. “Socialism with a (10 pts)",
        "human face” was promoted during this period by Alexander Dubcek [doob-check]. A Soviet invasion ended, what period of reform in 1968 in Czechoslovakia, named for its capital?"
      ],
      "answer": "Prague Spring"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man lost a battle along the Enipeus River after Titus Labienus’s cavalry were shocked by infantry with pikes. After Cicero gave the speech Pro Lege Manilia, this man replaced Lucius Lucullus as commander in the (20 pts)",
        "Mithridatic Wars. The Lex Gabinia gave this man power to put down Cilician piracy in the Mediterranean. Ptolemy XIII ordered the death of this (10 pts)",
        "Roman in Egypt after he lost at the Battle of Pharsalus. For ten points, the First Triumvirate was composed of Marcus Crassus, Julius Caesar, and which man?"
      ],
      "answer": "Pompey the Great"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Schools called Nizamiyyah were established in this empire, whose rulers sought guidance from a vizier’s manual, the “Book of Government.” This empire’s founder, Tughril, won the Battle of Dandanaqan over the (20 pts)",
        "Ghaznavids. An entity administered by this empire was rivaled by the Danishmends and lost to the Mongols at the Battle of Kose Dag. That offshoot of this empire, the (10 pts)",
        "Sultanate of Rum, was created after Byzantine Emperor Romanos IV was captured at the Battle of Manzikert. Malik Shah I and Alp Arslan once ruled, for ten points, what empire that was founded in 1037 and based in Anatolia?"
      ],
      "answer": "Seljuk Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After losing the Battle of Stilo, a king of this name faced a rebellion called the Great Slav Uprising led by the Wendish people. With Conrad the Red, a king of this name ended the Magyar invasion of Bavaria by the chieftain (20 pts)",
        "Bulcsu [BULL-choo] at a 955 battle. That king with this name agreed to be the secular protector of the Holy See, starting the (10 pts)",
        "Holy Roman Empire. For ten points, give this name of a “Great” German king who was the son of Henry the Fowler and who defeated the Hungarians at Lechfeld."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Otto",
        "Otto the Great",
        "Otto I, II, and/or III"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler ordered Gnaeus Corbulo to invade Armenia, which nearly sparked a war with Vologases I’s Parthian Empire. Suetonius suppressed (20 pts)",
        "Boudicca’s revolt during the reign of this man. The Domus Aurea was commissioned by this man, who may have orchestrated a (10 pts)",
        "disaster in his capital to make room for it. The Year of the Four Emperors began after the assassination of this man, whose popularity plummeted due to a 64 AD fire. For ten points, name this emperor accused of fiddling while Rome burned."
      ],
      "answer": "Nero Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this city, Cleombrotus I, was killed at the 371 BC Battle of Leuctra. A fleet from this city, under the command of (20 pts)",
        "Lysander, won the Battle of Aegospotami near the end of the Peloponnesian War. In this city, Cinadon attempted to overthrow the (10 pts)",
        "Eurypontid King Agesilaus II with the help of the helots. Three hundred soldiers from this city fought a valiant battle against invading Persian forces at the Battle of Thermopylae. Leonidas led, for ten points, what Greek city-state, the arch-rival to Athens?"
      ],
      "answer": "Sparta"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This treaty led to a controversy over whether Mecklenburg had to concede more than the city of Wismar. A peace that this treaty failed to ensure was finally brokered in the Peace of Pyrenees. Swiss independence from the (20 pts)",
        "Holy Roman Empire was formally established by this treaty, which also led the Dutch Republic to be formally recognized by (10 pts)",
        "Spain and reaffirmed the principles of the Peace of Augsburg. For ten points, name this treaty that was signed in Osnabruck and Munster and ended the Thirty Years War."
      ],
      "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Stuart Mill claimed that this battle, “even as an event in British history, is more important than the Battle of Hastings.” Ctesias [tee-sus] and Herodotus disagree over whether a general who had earlier sacked Eretria, Datis, was (20 pts)",
        "killed at this battle. Eleven Plataeans were killed at this battle, where troops of the Leontis tribe were commanded by Themistocles. (10 pts)",
        "Miltiades [mill-TIE-uh-deez] led the winners of this battle, after which Pheidippides [fay-uh-DIP-uh-deez] delivered the news to Athens. For ten points, name this 490 BC battle that inspired a modern 26 mile race."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man won the Mallian campaign, personally killing their leader but sustaining a nearly fatal arrow wound in the process. Previously, this man had defeated Ariobarzanes at the Battle of the Persian Gates and Batis at the Siege of (20 pts)",
        "Gaza. This man led the charge which won the Battle of Chaeronea, and his other victories include the Battle of the Granicus River, the Battle of Issus, and the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Gaugamela, where he defeated King Darius III of Persia and brought an end to the Persian empire. For ten points, name this Macedonian conqueror."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alexander the Great",
        "Alexander III of Macedon T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man took power when his mentor Ephialtes was murdered in 461 BC. This man A died from the plague along with both of his legitimate sons, prompting (20 pts)",
        "Athens to change his own law and allow his half-Athenian son to be a citizen. This man led Athens in the First Peloponnesian War and became known as its (10 pts)",
        "“First Citizen.” For ten points, name this orator, general, and statesman who sought to promote democracy during the “Golden Age of Athens.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Pericles"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Known as heket to the Egyptians, this good fills the \"mouth of a perfectly contented man,\" according to a 23rd century BC proverb. Shorting a customer of this substance is punishable by (20 pts)",
        "drowning per the Code of Hammurabi, and the Sumerians drank a thick version of this beverage through a straw. Cereals like barley and (10 pts)",
        "wheat are used to make, for ten points, what ancient alcoholic drink often made at a brewery?"
      ],
      "answer": "Beer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The body of this nation'sKingAlexanderIwasthrownoffabalconyofthe\"Old Palace\" during its May Coup, whichreplacedhimwithPeterI.AlongsideRomaniaand Greece, this nation seized territory from Bulgaria during (20 pts)",
        "the Second Balkan War. Austria-Hungary gave this smaller nation the JulyUltimatumafternationalistGavrilo Princip killed Archduke FranzFerdinandinBosnia (10 pts)",
        ".Fortenpoints,namethisBalkan nation, the most populous constituent of the former Yugoslavia."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic ofSerbiaor RepublikaSrbija",
        "acceptKingdom ofSerbia",
        "or Kraljevina Srbija"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Exposure to the chemical Pyridostigmine [[\"pie\"-rih-doh-STIG-meen]] Bromide led to this war's namesake \"syndrome,\" a debilitating chronic illness common among U.S. (20 pts)",
        "veterans. The end of this war's hostilities have partially been attributed to photos released of the Highway of Death. This month-long war used the codename Desert Storm. The invasion of (10 pts)",
        "Kuwait by Iraq triggered, for ten points, what U.S.-led invasion during the George H.W. Bush administration?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "First Persian Gulf War",
        "Gulf War Syndrome",
        "First Iraq War before mentioned",
        "Desert Storm before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this province, the Solidarity Coalition led by Jack Munro led a general strike in the early 1980s made up of 100,000 strikers. The Tsimshian [[sihm-SHE-ahn]] people of this province built totem poles and hosted potlach [[POT-latch]] (20 pts)",
        "ceremonies. The term \"Fifty-Four Forty or Fight\" concerned the border dispute between the Oregon territory and this modern province. Royal Navy officer George Vancouver names (10 pts)",
        "the largest city of, for ten points, what Canadian province?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "British Columbia",
        "BC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This type of government was established following the successive overthrow of Hippias [[HIP-ee-us]] and the Spartan-favoring oligarchy of Isagoras [[iss- ah-GOH- russ]] in favor of Cleisthenes's [[KLYS-thin-eez-is]] reforms. This (20 pts)",
        "government style, for which Solon laid the foundations, included a punishment called ostracism, and was available to all citizens, though that excluded women and (10 pts)",
        "slaves. For ten points, name this isonomic government style that was adopted by ancient Athens, in which citizens governed themselves directly."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Athenian Democracy",
        "Demokratia",
        "Democratic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Albert Einstein proved this statement using dissection without rearrangement, and James A. Garfield proved this statement using a trapezoid. For a Cartesian coordinate plane, the (20 pts)",
        "Euclidean distance formula can be derived from this statement. A Babylonian tablet called Plimpton 322 is the oldest known record of (10 pts)",
        "\"triples\" derived from this theorem that include examples such as (3,4,5) and (5,12,13). For ten points, what is this formula stated as \"A squared plus B squared equals C squared,\" named from a Greek philosopher?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Pythagorean theorem or Pythagoras's theorem",
        "Pythagorean triples",
        "\"equation\" in place of \"theorem\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In thisempire,theChakitakllawasafootplowusedbyfarmersduetoalackof large pack animals. This state employed chasqui [[CHAH-skee]] couriers, who kept record of transactions using the quipu [[KEE-poo]] knotted-string (20 pts)",
        "system. This empire experienced a civil war between Huascar and Atahualpa [[ah-tah-HWAHL-pah]]priortoitsconquestbytheSpanish. (10 pts)",
        "Fortenpoints,namethis Andean empire that was conquered in 1533 by Francisco Pizarro. ANSWER:Incan Empire (or theIncas; acceptTawantinsuyu;orRealm of the Four Parts; orFour Parts Together) 2021-22 C Set History (5) This politician and his wife, Lou, nursed injured soldiers in Tianjin [[TYAHN-JIN]] during the Boxer Rebellion. Douglas MacArthur ignored this president's order to halt the tear-gassing and eviction of the Bonus Army (+) camp under the guisethattheveteransplannedtooverthrowthegovernment.Shantytowns during the early Great Depression were named for this president. The Wall Street Crash of 1929 (*) occurred during, for ten points, what Republican's single presidential term?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "HerbertHooveror Herbert ClarkHoover",
        "acceptHoovervilles"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The EcclesiasticalOrdinancesofKingCnut[[CAH-noot]]definedcertainlawsso that these \"madly audacious\" creatures \"do not too widely devastate, nor bite too many of the spiritual flock.\" The geographer Pausanias [[pow-SAY-nee-us]] described how King (20 pts)",
        "Lycaon [[\"lie\"-KAY-on]] became oneofthesecreaturesaftersacrificinga child to Zeus. Modern fiction describes these monstersasbeingvulnerabletoobjects cast from (10 pts)",
        "silver. For ten points, name these historically-feared creaturesthattransform into dangerous canines during the full moon. ANSWER:Werewolf(orLycanthrope; prompt on \"wolf\";prompt on \"shapeshifter\"; accept plurals) (4) Early attempts tosailthisrouteincludedattemptstofindthemythicalStraitof Anián [[ah-nee-AHN]], which was allegedly traversed by Juan de Fuca. Thisroutewas the intended goal of John (+) Cabot's east-west voyage, as well as Jacques Cartier's expedition into the Gulf of Saint Lawrence. Robert McClure was the first to sail this ice-bound (*) route from 1850 to 1854. For ten points, name this sea route between that Atlantic and Pacific Oceans that crosses through the Arctic. ANSWER:Northwest Passage(accept word forms; acceptdescriptive answers before \"Atlantic\") 2021-22 C Set History (5) A ruler of this empire produced the Kandahar [[KAN-dah-har]] Inscription, written in Aramaic and Greek, to encourage foreigners toadopt\"Dharma.\"SeleucusI Nicator [[seh-LOO-kas \"the first\" neh-KAY-tor]] sent the diplomat (+) Megasthenes [[meh-GAS-theh-nees]] to this empire's court, resulting in the ethnography Indika. Much of the Deccan Plateau region was conquered and held by this empire's ruler Bindusara. The Buddhist convert (*) Ashoka ruled, for ten points, what ancient Indian empire founded by Chandragupta [[chahn-drah-GOOP-tah]]? ANSWER:Mauryan Empire (or theMauryans; acceptMuriyaKala) (6) A fake story suggested Ronald Reagan was intended to play the lead in this historical fiction movie. This film was released early to capitalize on free press from Operation (+) Torch, the allied invasion of North Africa. This movie ends with Louis suggesting he join the Free French with Rick Blaine, who states, \"I think this is the beginning of a (*) beautiful friendship.\" For ten points, what Humphrey Bogart andIngrid Bergman Best Picture winner is named for a Moroccan city? ANSWER:Casablanca (7) This man lost a Connecticut congressional run to his cousin and future chairman of the DNC, William Henry. This man purported that a former enslaved person named Joice Heth was, in fact, the 161 year old nurse (+) of George Washington. This man, who unveiled the first aquarium in the U.S., hiredperformers (*) such as the dwarf Tom Thumb andtheoperaticsingerJennyLind.JamesAnthonyBailey paired with, for ten points, which showman to create a namesake 20th century circus?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "P.T.Barnumor Phineas TaylorBarnum",
        "acceptRingling Brothers &Barnum and Bailey Circus"
      ]
    }
  ]
}